<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A book of warnings, or, The visitation of the Lord's love to the King and his Parliament, the nobility and gentry, the arch-bishops and bishops &amp;c., the presbytery, the Independents and Baptists, the people of these nations thorough [sic] his servant George Bishope.</title>
            <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2988</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18647</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12258252</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12258252</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57623</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28227)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 167:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A book of warnings, or, The visitation of the Lord's love to the King and his Parliament, the nobility and gentry, the arch-bishops and bishops &amp;c., the presbytery, the Independents and Baptists, the people of these nations thorough [sic] his servant George Bishope.</title>
                  <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Warnings.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57623:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57623:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A Book of Warnings OR, THE VISITATION OF THE LORD'S Love</p>
            <list>
               <head>To</head>
               <item>The KING and his PARLIAMENT.</item>
               <item>The NOBILITY and GENTRY.</item>
               <item>The ARCH-BISHOPS and BISHOPS. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>The PRESBYTERY.</item>
               <item>The INDEPENDENTS and BAPTISTS.</item>
               <item>The PEOPLE of theſe Nations.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Thorough His Servant GEORGE BISHOPE.</p>
            <q>
               <p>But the end of all things is at hand, be ye therefore ſober, and watch unto Prayer, <bibl>1 Pet. 4. 7.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for Robert Wilſon, and are to be ſold at the Black-ſpread Eagle and Wind-Mill in Martins Le Grand, 1661.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57623:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57623:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the <hi>KING,</hi> and <hi>both</hi> Houſes of <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU <hi>have time to Work, and it is</hi> not <hi>long: The</hi> Lord <hi>hath been</hi> very <hi>Gracious unto</hi> you, <hi>and Done for</hi> you <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove What</hi> ye <hi>were able to</hi> Ask <hi>or</hi> Think, <hi>as it is at</hi> this <hi>Day;</hi> He <hi>hath Repleniſhed</hi> Your <hi>Sorrows and</hi> Troubles <hi>with</hi> Joy <hi>and</hi> Peace, <hi>and made</hi> Your <hi>Dominion larger than</hi> Ye <hi>could Wiſh: What is there that</hi> Your <hi>hearts can reaſonably ask, that</hi> You <hi>have not? Was ever</hi> Such <hi>a Day ſeen by a</hi> People, <hi>as by</hi> You? <hi>Was ever</hi> ſuch <hi>a Wonder wrought to make</hi> You <hi>ſo? Did the</hi> Earth <hi>ever know the like? Or can the</hi> Records <hi>of</hi> Ages <hi>parallel</hi> it? <hi>Was</hi> it <hi>not as much beyond</hi> Your <hi>thoughts (and that not long ſince) as</hi> You <hi>are above</hi> Your <hi>Enemies? Could</hi> Ye <hi>have thought that</hi> Ye <hi>ſhould be</hi> Rulers <hi>over</hi> theſe <hi>Nations, and ſo as at</hi> this <hi>Day, ſome</hi> few <hi>years ſince? Was it not Done in a</hi> Moment, <hi>as it were, without</hi> Blood <hi>or</hi> Price <hi>of</hi> War, <hi>which brought, and long kept</hi> Ye <hi>under? How</hi> calm? <hi>How</hi> ſtill? <hi>How in</hi> ſubjection <hi>are</hi> theſe <hi>Nations at</hi> this <hi>Day? Have</hi> Ye <hi>an Enemy? Can</hi> Ye <hi>think of one that can hurt</hi> You? <hi>The</hi> Hearts, <hi>the</hi> Perſons, <hi>the</hi> Purſes <hi>of the</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralitie <hi>of the</hi> Nations <hi>are Under</hi> You. <hi>A</hi> large <hi>Dominion; a</hi> goodly <hi>Heritage;</hi> England, <hi>the</hi> faireſt <hi>and</hi> beſt <hi>of</hi> Nations; <hi>England the</hi> moſt <hi>ſecure and</hi> ſafe <hi>of</hi> Nations: <hi>England the</hi> fatteſt <hi>and</hi> moſt <hi>fertile of the</hi> Nations: <hi>Men</hi> prompt, <hi>and</hi> ready, <hi>and</hi> bold, <hi>and</hi> active: A Seed Plot of Underſtanding; <hi>An</hi> Academy <hi>of</hi> Learning; <hi>A</hi> Nation <hi>of</hi> Men; <hi>A</hi> Warlike <hi>Nation; A</hi> People <hi>whom the</hi> Lord <hi>hath owned</hi> above <hi>any people. A</hi> People <hi>whom the</hi> Lord <hi>hath appeared to ſave,</hi> more <hi>than</hi> any <hi>people; A</hi> people <hi>whom</hi> He <hi>hath ſought to gather, whom</hi> He <hi>hath gathered (many of</hi> them) <hi>into</hi> his <hi>Reſt, and who know the</hi> Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is</hi> your <hi>ſtate, this</hi> your <hi>Condition; and</hi> thus <hi>hath the</hi> Lord <hi>done for</hi> you, <hi>that</hi> ye <hi>may obſerve</hi> his <hi>Statutes, and keep</hi> his <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57623:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>that</hi> ye <hi>may live, and it may be well with</hi> you <hi>and</hi> your <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity after</hi> you, <hi>and that</hi> ye <hi>may know</hi> his <hi>Reſt, which is</hi> Eternal, <hi>as</hi> he <hi>hath given</hi> you <hi>here a Reſt</hi> temporal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> now, <hi>what doth the</hi> Lord <hi>require of</hi> you? <hi>but that</hi> you <hi>Do Juſtly, and</hi> love <hi>Mercy, and</hi> walk <hi>humbly with</hi> God; <hi>that</hi> you <hi>break</hi> every <hi>yoke, and unbind</hi> every <hi>burden, and let the</hi> Oppreſſed <hi>go free: That</hi> you <hi>love</hi> Juſtice <hi>and</hi> Judgement; <hi>that</hi> you <hi>rule for</hi> God, <hi>who hath brought</hi> you <hi>into</hi> Rule, <hi>and hitherto preſerved</hi> you: <hi>That</hi> you <hi>take not upon</hi> you <hi>to Rule over</hi> his <hi>Kingdom, or to preſcribe to</hi> his <hi>Dominion;</hi> Whoſe <hi>Kingdom is an</hi> everlaſting <hi>Kingdom, and</hi> his <hi>Dominion that which ſhall</hi> never <hi>have end, that of</hi> him <hi>in the</hi> Conſcience: <hi>That</hi> ye <hi>make not</hi> his <hi>innocent</hi> people <hi>to ſuffer, who ſuffered with</hi> you, <hi>and by, and under</hi> your <hi>Enemies; who have</hi> good will <hi>towards</hi> you <hi>and</hi> all <hi>men; though</hi> they <hi>war with the</hi> Spirit <hi>of</hi> iniquity <hi>which holds</hi> Mens <hi>ſouls in</hi> Captivity, <hi>with</hi> Weapons <hi>that are not</hi> Carnal, <hi>but</hi> Spiritual; <hi>who deſire</hi> your <hi>everlaſting welfare; and that it may be well with</hi> you <hi>and</hi> yours <hi>for ever; who are</hi> inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>as to</hi> you, <hi>neither hath there been any ill-will found in</hi> them <hi>againſt</hi> you, <hi>in</hi> thought <hi>or in</hi> deed; <hi>who are</hi> peaceable <hi>in the</hi> Land, <hi>and ſeated in it by</hi> Natural <hi>Right; who conſiſt of</hi> Many <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of</hi> Families, Men, Women, Children <hi>and</hi> Servants, Natural <hi>Engliſh; who</hi> wrong <hi>no</hi> man; <hi>who</hi> reſiſt <hi>not</hi> Evil; <hi>who are</hi> good <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of</hi> Holineſs, <hi>of</hi> Virtue, <hi>of</hi> Temperance, <hi>and</hi> Teſtimonies <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Evil; <hi>which cauſeth the</hi> Wrath <hi>of</hi> God <hi>to</hi> come <hi>upon</hi> Nations, <hi>and to</hi> afflict <hi>and</hi> deſtroy them, Whoſe <hi>Deſire is that</hi> none <hi>may pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but that</hi> all <hi>might come to the</hi> knowledge <hi>of the</hi> truth: <hi>The Lord God hath called</hi> them; <hi>the Lord God is with</hi> them; <hi>the</hi> Lord God <hi>hath</hi> kept, <hi>and will</hi> keep them, <hi>as</hi> they <hi>abide with</hi> him: <hi>The</hi> Lord God <hi>hath</hi> made them <hi>to ſtand, and will</hi> make them: He <hi>hath made</hi> them <hi>a</hi> People, <hi>and</hi> they <hi>ſhall be ſo:</hi> He <hi>hath obſerved</hi> all <hi>that hath been done</hi> for, <hi>and againſt</hi> them; <hi>and</hi> he <hi>hath recompenced, and will recompence</hi> it; they <hi>fear before</hi> him; they <hi>dare not diſpleaſe</hi> him; they <hi>may not ſet up</hi> Man <hi>above</hi> him; they <hi>muſt obey</hi> him <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> man; they <hi>obey</hi> man <hi>in</hi> him: He <hi>cannot ſee</hi> them <hi>wronged, and not require it;</hi> they <hi>are</hi> his <hi>Jewels,</hi> (his <hi>People are) and as the</hi> Apple <hi>of</hi> his <hi>eye:</hi> He <hi>that toucheth</hi> you, <hi>toucheth the</hi> Apple <hi>of</hi> mine <hi>eye, ſaith the</hi> Lord; they <hi>tremble before</hi> him, <hi>and of</hi> him <hi>ſtand in awe, who is</hi> Lord <hi>of</hi> Heaven <hi>and</hi> Earth; they <hi>fear not</hi> man <hi>whoſe</hi> breath <hi>is in</hi> his <hi>Noſtrils, becauſe</hi> they <hi>may not:</hi> Their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57623:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>fear towards</hi> him <hi>is not taught by the</hi> precepts <hi>of</hi> men, <hi>becauſe it ought not;</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>ſaith ſo,</hi> Matt: 15. 7, 8, 9. Ye Hypocrites, <hi>ſaith</hi> he <hi>to the</hi> Phariſees) well did Eſaias propheſie of you, ſaying, This people draw nigh unto me with their mouth, and honoreth me with their lips, but their heart is far from me; But in vain do they worſhip me, teaching for Doctrine the <hi>[Traditions]</hi> of men. <hi>And the</hi> Lord <hi>by</hi> his <hi>Prophet,</hi> Iſa. 29 13, 14. Wherefore the Lord ſaid, Foraſmuch as this people draw near me with their mouth, and with their lips do honor me, but have removed their <hi>heart</hi> far from me, and their fear towards me is taught by the [Precepts] of men. Therefore behold, I will proceed to do a marvellous Work amongſt this people, and a wonder; for the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of their wiſe men ſhall periſh, and the Underſtanding of their Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſhall be hid. They <hi>worſhip</hi> God <hi>in</hi> ſpirit <hi>and in</hi> truth, <hi>neither in</hi> this <hi>Mountain, nor yet at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>becauſe the</hi> Father <hi>ſeeketh</hi> ſuch <hi>to worſhip</hi> him; <hi>whom the</hi> Son <hi>ſaith will be</hi> ſo <hi>worſhipped.</hi> God. is a Spirit <hi>(ſaith</hi> he) and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth. Woman believe me, the hour cometh when ye ſhall neither in this Mountain, nor yet at Jeruſalem, worſhip the Father: Ye worſhip ye know not what; we know what we Worſhip; for ſalvation is of the Jews: But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in ſpirit and in truth, for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him, <hi>John</hi> 4. 21, 22, 23, 24. They <hi>cannot</hi> bow <hi>to</hi> any <hi>thing but</hi> what's <hi>of the</hi> Lord <hi>in</hi> his <hi>Worſhip, becauſe the</hi> Lord <hi>hath</hi> ſworn, As I live ſaith the Lord, every knee ſhall bow to me, and every tongue ſhall confeſs to God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 11. They <hi>cannot</hi> owe <hi>their</hi> Conſciences <hi>to</hi> any <hi>but to</hi> God, <hi>becauſe</hi> He <hi>is</hi> Lord <hi>of</hi> Conſcience: They <hi>cannot but</hi> meet <hi>together to</hi> Worſhip <hi>God, and to</hi> wait <hi>upon</hi> him; <hi>becauſe</hi> they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another, and the Lord hearkned and heard it, and a Book of Remembrance was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before him for them that feared the Lord, and thought on his Name; and they ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, in that day when I make up my Jewels, and I will spare them as a man ſpareth his own ſon that ſerveth him, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 15, 16. And not forſaking the aſſembling of our ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is, but exhorting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo much the more as you ſee the day approaching, <hi>Heb</hi> 10. 25. They <hi>cannot</hi> ſwear, <hi>becauſe</hi> Chriſt <hi>ſaith,</hi> Swear not at all, neither by Heaven, for its God's throne; neither by the Earth, for it is his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool; neither by Jeruſalem, for it is the City of the Great King; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhalt thou ſwear by thy Head, for thou canſt not make one hair
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57623:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> white or black: But let your communication be Yea, Yea, Nay, Nay, for whatſoever is more then theſe, cometh of evil, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. 34, 35<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 36, 37. <hi>And</hi> his <hi>Apoſtle</hi> James <hi>ſaith,</hi> But above all things my Brethren, ſwear not, neither by Heaven, neither by the Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, neither by any other Oath: But let your yea be yea, and your nay nay, leſt ye fall into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>And the</hi> ſwearing <hi>[by] any thing, was that which made it an</hi> Oath; <hi>and</hi> they <hi>uſed in</hi> their <hi>ſwearing to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on [by] ſomething, which made it an</hi> Oath; <hi>and</hi> they <hi>were gone (many of them) from that of the</hi> Law, <hi>(which</hi> Chriſt <hi>the</hi> end <hi>of the</hi> Law <hi>for</hi> Righteouſneſs, <hi>alſo repeals, in that</hi> he <hi>ſaith,</hi> Ye have heard it hath been ſaid by them of Old time, Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but ſhalt perform unto the Lord thine Oath's; but I ſay unto you, Swear not at all, &amp;c. <hi>as aforeſaid) which</hi> Law <hi>required</hi> them <hi>to ſwear, and to</hi> ſwear <hi>by the</hi> Lord: Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve him, and ſwear By his Name, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 13. <hi>I ſay,</hi> they <hi>were gone from that of the</hi> law, <hi>which required</hi> them <hi>when</hi> they <hi>ſwore, to</hi> ſwear <hi>[by] the</hi> Lord; Thou ſhalt ſwear the Lord liveth in truth, in judgement, and in righteouſneſs, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>and</hi> ſwore <hi>[by] the</hi> Lord, <hi>and [by]</hi> Malcom, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>And,</hi> they taught my people to ſwear <hi>[by]</hi> Baal, <hi>Jer.</hi> 12. 16. <hi>And</hi> they that ſwear <hi>[by]</hi> the ſin of Samaria, and ſay, thy God O Dan liveth; and the Manner of Beerſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba <hi>(the</hi> Calves <hi>there by which</hi> they <hi>worſhipt God)</hi> liveth, even they ſhall fall, and never riſe up again, <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 14. <hi>And [by the</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>and [by] the</hi> Earth, <hi>and [by]</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He <hi>repeals it all:</hi> But I ſay unto you, ſwear not at all; <hi>neither [by] the</hi> Lord, <hi>nor</hi> any <hi>other thing:</hi> Swear not at all, I ſay unto you <hi>ſo, though</hi> ye have heard it hath been ſaid by them of old time, Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but ſhalt perform to the <hi>[Lord]</hi> thine Oaths. <hi>This was not</hi> Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorie <hi>ſwearing, or in ordinary Communication (as people would have it, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſome ſay ſo, but without</hi> proof) <hi>for it appears not that</hi> there <hi>was any ſuch kind of</hi> ſwearing <hi>among the</hi> Jews, <hi>for they were not to take his Name in vain; but</hi> ſuch <hi>Oath's as were made to</hi> God, ſolemn <hi>Oaths, (as</hi> I <hi>may ſo ſay) by which</hi> they <hi>bound</hi> their <hi>ſouls to</hi> God <hi>to perform, as it was</hi> then <hi>required; and when</hi> they <hi>ſwore ſo,</hi> they <hi>mentioned [by] ſomething (as</hi> I <hi>have ſaid) and this [By] made it an</hi> Oath; <hi>and that which</hi> they <hi>ſwore [by] was to be that which was</hi> Paramount <hi>to</hi> all, <hi>and could</hi> witneſs, <hi>and was</hi> able to avenge, <hi>which the</hi> Lord <hi>was onely, therefore</hi> they <hi>were to mention</hi> his <hi>Name when</hi> they <hi>ſwore; and it was a</hi> figure <hi>of</hi> ſomething <hi>which</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57623:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>was to</hi> come, <hi>which was not</hi> then <hi>come,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>(whom that</hi> Nation, <hi>and the</hi> Body <hi>of</hi> all <hi>that</hi> worſhip <hi>and</hi> ſervice <hi>typified, and which had</hi> their <hi>end in</hi> him, <hi>and which</hi> he <hi>when</hi> he <hi>was come, put</hi> thus <hi>an</hi> end <hi>unto; who is the</hi> Oath <hi>of</hi> God—to perform the mercy promiſed to our fathers, and to remember his holy Covenant, the Oath which he ſware to our Father Abraham that he would grant unto us, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 72, 73, 74<hi>—And who it is that</hi> binds <hi>the</hi> ſoul <hi>to</hi> God: <hi>In</hi> whom <hi>all the</hi> promiſes <hi>of</hi> God <hi>are</hi> Yea <hi>and</hi> Amen; <hi>Even in</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, 2 Cor. 1, 20. <hi>who ſaith,</hi> But <hi>I</hi> ſay unto you, Swear not at all: <hi>And</hi> he <hi>that ſaid ſo, is the</hi> ſame <hi>that ſaid,</hi> Whoſoever is angry with his Brother without a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of the Judgement, &amp;c. And whoſoever looketh on a woman to luſt after her, hath committed Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery with her already in his heart <hi>in the</hi> ſame <hi>Ch.</hi> Mat. 5. They <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not maintain a</hi> Prieſthood <hi>by</hi> tythes, <hi>becauſe</hi> that <hi>Prieſthood which had the</hi> tythes <hi>is done away, and ended in</hi> him <hi>to whom</hi> Abraham <hi>paid</hi> tythes, <hi>in</hi> Melchizedeck, <hi>who is a</hi> Prieſt for ever after the Order of Melchizedeck, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 4. <hi>whom</hi> it <hi>figured.</hi> They <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not maintain</hi> temples <hi>of</hi> ſtone, <hi>or come to</hi> Worſhip <hi>in</hi> them, <hi>as</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>conſecrated by</hi> man; <hi>or becauſe</hi> they <hi>have in</hi> them, <hi>more than</hi> other <hi>places, or for that</hi> God <hi>is more to be</hi> found <hi>in</hi> them, <hi>or wil be</hi> found <hi>in</hi> them; <hi>or that</hi> he <hi>hath</hi> ſo <hi>ſignified more than in</hi> other <hi>pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; or that</hi> he <hi>will be preſent: Becauſe</hi> God dwelleth not in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples made with hands, neither is worſhipped with mens hands. God that made the world, and all things therein, ſeeing that he is Lord of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, dwelleth not in temples made with hands, neither is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped with mens hands, as though he needed any thing, ſeeing that he giveth unto all, life, and breath, and all things, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 24, 25. <hi>And the</hi> temple <hi>at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>was a</hi> figure <hi>of</hi> him <hi>who was to</hi> come, <hi>which is ended in</hi> him <hi>who is</hi> come. <hi>And now the</hi> temple <hi>of</hi> God <hi>is</hi> thoſe <hi>in whom the</hi> Holy Ghoſt <hi>dwelleth.</hi> Know ye not that ye are the temple of God, and that the ſpirit of God dwelleth in you? If any man defile the temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy, for the temple of God is holy, which temple ye are, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 16 17. <hi>And,</hi> what agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath the temple of God with idols? For ye are the temple of the living God, as God hath ſaid, <hi>I</hi> will dwell in them, and walk in them; and <hi>I</hi> will be their God, and they ſhall be my people; Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeperate, ſaith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing, &amp; <hi>I</hi> wil receive you, &amp; wil be a Father unto you, and ye ſhall be my ſons and daughters, ſaith the Lord God Almighty, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:57623:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 6. 16, 17, 18. They <hi>cannot be in the</hi> Obſervation <hi>of</hi> Daies <hi>and times ſet in the</hi> will <hi>of</hi> man; <hi>Becauſe ſuch things alſo had</hi> their Day, <hi>and</hi> End; <hi>even</hi> thoſe <hi>which were commanded of the</hi> Lord; Ye obſerve Daies, and Months, &amp; Times, &amp; Years; <hi>I</hi> am afraid of you, leſt <hi>I</hi> have beſtowed upon you labour in vain, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 10, 11. <hi>And,</hi> let no man therefore judge you in Meat, or in Drink, or in reſpect of a Holy-day; <hi>or</hi> of the New-Moon, <hi>or,</hi> of the Sabbath-Dayes, which are a ſhadow of things to come, but the Body is of Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 16, 17. <hi>And,</hi> He that regardeth a Day, regardeth it unto the Lord; <hi>and,</hi> he that doth not regard the Day unto the Lord, he doth not regard it. He that Eateth, Eateth to the Lord, for he giveth God thanks; and he that eateth not unto the Lord, he eateth not, and giveth God thanks. For none of Us liveth to himſelf, and no man dieth to himſelf. For, whether we live, we live unto the Lord; and whether we die, we die unto the Lord; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we live therefore, or die, we are the Lord's. For to this end Chriſt both Died and roſe and revived, that he might be Lord both of the Dead and Living. But why doeſt thou judge thy Brother? Or, why doeſt thou ſet at nought thy Brother? We ſhall all ſtand before the Judgment ſeat of Chriſt; As it is written, As <hi>I</hi> live, ſaith the Lord, Every knee ſhall bow to me, and every tongue ſhall confeſs to God. So then every One of Us ſhall give account of himſelf to God. Let us not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore judge one another any more, but judge this rather, that no man put a ſtumbling block, or occaſion to fall, in his brother's way. <hi>I</hi> know, and am perſwaded by the Lord Jeſus, that there is nothing unclean of it ſelf, but to him that eſteemeth any thing to be unclean, to him it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean. But if thy Brother be grieved with thy Meat, Now walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou not Charitably. Deſtroy not him with thy meat for whom Chriſt dyed. Let not then your good be evil ſpoken of. For the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God is not meat, and drink, but Righteouſneſs, and Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt. For he that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable to God, and approved of men. Let Us, therefore, follow after the things that make for Peace, and things wherewith we may edifie one a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her; for meat deſtroy not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e work of God; one man eſteemeth one day above another; Another eſteemeth every day alike. Let every man be fully perſwaded in his own mind, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 5. <hi>to the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now,</hi> theſe <hi>things</hi> I <hi>am moved of the</hi> Lord <hi>to lay before</hi> you; <hi>to the</hi> End <hi>that</hi> yee <hi>may take heed of</hi> Doing <hi>any thing by which the</hi> Lord <hi>may be</hi> Diſpleaſed <hi>with</hi> you; <hi>Or that may</hi> grieve his <hi>Spirit, or, make</hi> him <hi>to</hi> Repent <hi>of the</hi> good <hi>he hath done</hi> you;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57623:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>or to become</hi> your <hi>Enemy. For certainly if</hi> yee <hi>ſhall</hi> impoſe <hi>upon</hi> Conſcience <hi>in</hi> things <hi>appertaining to the</hi> Worſhip <hi>of</hi> God; <hi>or cauſe his Innocent</hi> People <hi>to ſuffer; or, not</hi> Anſwer <hi>the</hi> End <hi>of the</hi> Lord <hi>in giving</hi> you <hi>this</hi> Day <hi>and</hi> Tryal; His <hi>hand will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> you, <hi>and</hi> he <hi>will reckon</hi> theſe <hi>things with</hi> you; <hi>and it will be ſad for</hi> you <hi>in that Day; When</hi> he <hi>ſhall render unto</hi> you <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to</hi> your <hi>Works. And therefore in</hi> love <hi>to</hi> you, <hi>and in the</hi> fear <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>and as</hi> moved <hi>of him, and as deſiring</hi> your <hi>wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare both</hi> here <hi>and</hi> hereafter, I <hi>have written.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GEO. BISHOPE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>To the</hi> Nobility <hi>and</hi> Gentry <hi>of</hi> Theſe <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>YOur</hi> Opportunities are <hi>great</hi> to do Good; the <hi>Lord</hi> hath not dealt by <hi>You</hi> as with <hi>Other</hi> men; <hi>You</hi> have <hi>Eſtates</hi> Great and Large; <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Revenues,</hi> and many <hi>your</hi> Servants; in the moſt ſweet and <hi>flouriſhing</hi> Places of the <hi>Nation. You</hi> are Seated, and <hi>your</hi> World abounds: <hi>You</hi> have in a manner what <hi>yee</hi> can wiſh; and <hi>your</hi> Travel is little (moſt of you); from <hi>your</hi> Anceſtors <hi>yee</hi> have received from Generation to Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with <hi>little</hi> Toyl, or <hi>Trouble,</hi> as to <hi>you;</hi> unleſs <hi>your</hi> Deſire of Encreaſe, or falling below by <hi>other</hi> Miſcarriages hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned it: <hi>You</hi> are <hi>full</hi> of <hi>Eaſe</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure;</hi> and if <hi>any</hi> thing be of <hi>more</hi> De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ectableneſs then <hi>other, you</hi> have it; <hi>Ride</hi> in and out; <hi>Riſe, Walk, lie</hi> down at your pleaſure; when multitudes of <hi>others</hi> riſe early, and lye down late, and <hi>Eat</hi> the <hi>bread</hi> of <hi>care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,</hi> and are <hi>your</hi> ſervants.</p>
            <p>And this is the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>many,</hi> or <hi>moſt</hi> of <hi>you;</hi> and it is <hi>great</hi> and <hi>large</hi> as to the <hi>Outward,</hi> Who are like to <hi>you?</hi> Now, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns <hi>you</hi> to ſee how <hi>you</hi> Anſwer the <hi>Lord</hi> for <hi>all his</hi> kindneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and how <hi>yee</hi> Return to <hi>him</hi> according to the <hi>benefits</hi> received; For, the <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in <hi>all this</hi> is not that <hi>yee</hi> ſhould do as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57623:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>yee</hi> liſt, and becauſe <hi>yee</hi> have <hi>your</hi> Wills as to <hi>this</hi> World; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>yee</hi> ſhould do <hi>your</hi> Wills in <hi>this</hi> world; but the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>him</hi> that gave it <hi>you. Exceſs, Riot, Pride, Haughtineſs, Surfeting, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Gluttony, Wantonneſs, Curſing, Swearing, Diceing, Gaming, Chambering, Revelling, ſpending</hi> the <hi>Creatures</hi> on <hi>your</hi> Luſts, <hi>Living</hi> in <hi>pleaſure, loving</hi> of <hi>pleaſures more</hi> then <hi>God,</hi> with ſuch like; were not the <hi>things</hi> that <hi>he</hi> minded as <hi>his</hi> End who with a <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral</hi> hand hath miniſtred to <hi>you;</hi> but to be <hi>humble, ſober, meek, juſt, temperate; lovers</hi> of <hi>good</hi> things, <hi>lovers</hi> of <hi>God; liberal, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, given</hi> to <hi>good</hi> works, <hi>lovers</hi> of <hi>Hoſpitality, kind, virtuous, ſerving</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> without <hi>diſtraction; Paſſing</hi> the <hi>time</hi> of <hi>your</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journing <hi>here</hi> in fear. For, the <hi>Lord</hi> will require an account of <hi>you</hi> for all the <hi>deeds</hi> done in the <hi>body,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> judgment <hi>ye</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcape; and the more kind and <hi>liberal he</hi> hath been to <hi>you,</hi> and put it into <hi>your</hi> hands to <hi>do</hi> good, the more <hi>he</hi> will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at <hi>your</hi> hands: For, <hi>to whomſoever much is given, of him much will be required.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>Friends,</hi> it concerns <hi>you</hi> (as <hi>I</hi> have ſaid) to mind <hi>your</hi> ſtate, and ſee how it is with <hi>you;</hi> That within <hi>you</hi> which <hi>witneſſeth</hi> to <hi>God</hi> will ſhew <hi>you</hi> if <hi>you</hi> heed it, and become <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> thereunto; which knows <hi>your</hi> Up-riſings, and <hi>your</hi> Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſittings; the <hi>thoughts</hi> and <hi>intents</hi> of <hi>your</hi> hearts, and tries them; which is with <hi>you</hi> wherever <hi>you</hi> go, and wherever <hi>you</hi> lie down, and whatever <hi>you</hi> do; which is <hi>Gods</hi> witneſs, and takes <hi>account</hi> of <hi>all your</hi> Actions; and ſpeaks to <hi>you</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> and bids <hi>yee</hi> not to do the <hi>Abominable</hi> thing that <hi>his</hi> ſoul abhorrs; which judgeth <hi>yee</hi> for Evil; which ſhews <hi>yee</hi> Evil; which tells <hi>yee</hi> what <hi>yee</hi> ſhould do; and which will make up the <hi>Reckoning</hi> for <hi>God;</hi> and will leave <hi>you</hi> without excuſe in the <hi>Day</hi> that he ſhall <hi>Judge</hi> the <hi>Quick</hi> and the <hi>Dead,</hi> at <hi>his</hi> appearing and <hi>coming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Friends,</hi> this is of Concernment to <hi>You,</hi> that this be <hi>your</hi> friend; and that <hi>this</hi> anſwer for <hi>you</hi> in <hi>that</hi> Day, that <hi>yee</hi> have done the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and Anſwered the Requirings of <hi>his</hi> Spirit in <hi>you;</hi> and what it moved <hi>you</hi> from <hi>God. Well done thou good and faithful ſervant, Enter into thy Maſters Joy,</hi> will the <hi>Lord</hi> ſay then to <hi>that</hi> which hath <hi>Done his</hi> Will; and that will be a <hi>good</hi> word for <hi>you</hi> in the <hi>Day</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> when <hi>amazement</hi> and <hi>horror</hi> ſhall ſeiz upon <hi>all</hi> who know not <hi>God,</hi> neither <hi>yield</hi> Obedience to <hi>his</hi> God; and all faces ſhall gather <hi>Blackneſs,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57623:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Paleneſs;</hi> and the <hi>Mighty</hi> ſhall be <hi>afraid,</hi> and the <hi>Strong</hi> man ſhall <hi>weep</hi> bitterly, and the <hi>Heavens</hi> ſhall <hi>depart</hi> as a <hi>Scrowl,</hi> and the <hi>Elements</hi> melt with <hi>fervent</hi> heat; and the <hi>Earth,</hi> and the <hi>works</hi> thereof be <hi>burnt</hi> up; and <hi>Men</hi> at <hi>their Wits</hi> Ends, expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what the <hi>End</hi> of thoſe things will be; and an <hi>Eternal</hi> End abides it to <hi>every</hi> one, either of <hi>joy.</hi> or <hi>ſorrow,</hi> for <hi>ever</hi> and <hi>ever.</hi> But if it be <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> and that condemn <hi>you</hi> which ſhould be <hi>your</hi> Peace, and that plead againſt <hi>yee,</hi> which <hi>you</hi> ſhould <hi>now</hi> mind to plead for <hi>you</hi> in <hi>that</hi> Day; and be a <hi>Witneſs</hi> to the <hi>Lord</hi> that <hi>yee</hi> have not <hi>hearkned,</hi> nor <hi>heard,</hi> nor <hi>obeied,</hi> nor <hi>receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Inſtruction, nor drawn near to the <hi>Lord;</hi> but you would do as <hi>yee</hi> liſted, and ſerve your pleaſures more then <hi>God,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume <hi>his</hi> Creatures on <hi>your</hi> Luſts; and ſwear <hi>by,</hi> and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme <hi>his</hi> Name; and make no <hi>other</hi> uſe of your time, then to pleaſe <hi>your</hi> ſelves, and not the <hi>Lord;</hi> nor of your Eſtates, but in order thereunto; and <hi>your</hi> time be <hi>over,</hi> and the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Viſitation be <hi>cloſed</hi> up, and at an <hi>End,</hi> then it will be <hi>ſad</hi> indeed; and better it had been for <hi>you</hi> that <hi>you</hi> had <hi>never</hi> been born; when with Rich <hi>Dives,</hi> you, who have had in <hi>your</hi> life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time your Pleaſure, muſt be tormented for <hi>ever</hi> and <hi>ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, <hi>my Friends,</hi> whilſt <hi>yee</hi> have time mind it; Let not the <hi>gracious</hi> hour of the <hi>Lord's</hi> tender Viſitation paſs Over <hi>you;</hi> but be <hi>yee</hi> gathred unto it: Come into <hi>his Arms</hi> now <hi>they</hi> are Open; approach unto <hi>him,</hi> now that <hi>he</hi> calls upon <hi>you.</hi> It's <hi>your</hi> need, not <hi>his,</hi> that makes him call on <hi>you:</hi> Come to <hi>him</hi> when <hi>he</hi> calls; <hi>He</hi> knows <hi>your</hi> ſtate; <hi>He</hi> knows what it will be for <hi>you</hi> to be <hi>Undone</hi> for <hi>ever; He</hi> knows the power of his wrath, though man doth not; <hi>He</hi> knows how it will <hi>ſink;</hi> how it will lay Low; how it will <hi>bring</hi> to the <hi>duſt;</hi> how it will <hi>bow</hi> the <hi>Pride</hi> of <hi>Man;</hi> and lay <hi>his</hi> Haughtineſs in the <hi>Duſt;</hi> and how <hi>intollerable</hi> it is. <hi>He</hi> calls that <hi>yee</hi> may hear whilſt <hi>yee</hi> have time; <hi>He</hi> calls that <hi>your</hi> ſouls may live: <hi>Why will yee die, O houſe of Iſrael? Return, and your ſouls ſhall live: He</hi> deſires not <hi>your</hi> death; he hath ſworn it; This is a <hi>teſtimonie</hi> of it, that <hi>he</hi> calls upon <hi>you;</hi> and that <hi>he</hi> calls upon <hi>you, you</hi> know; becauſe <hi>yee</hi> find <hi>that</hi> in <hi>you</hi> which ſhews <hi>yee</hi> Evil, and judges <hi>yee</hi> for Evil, and tells <hi>yee</hi> what <hi>yee</hi> ſhould do, and Anſwers to what <hi>I</hi> have ſaid to <hi>you:</hi> And, <hi>this is the power of God to ſalvation to as many as believe in it, and obey it. It's</hi> ſtronger then the <hi>Powers</hi> of <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57623:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> It <hi>ſteps</hi> thorough it; It <hi>comes</hi> before it; it <hi>ſhews yee</hi> what the <hi>Enemy</hi> is doing; and where <hi>he</hi> is <hi>leading you;</hi> and what's the <hi>Path;</hi> and whither it <hi>tends;</hi> and <hi>ſhines</hi> before <hi>you</hi> for <hi>you</hi> to ſee the <hi>Path</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> &amp; to <hi>walk</hi> in it; &amp; it will <hi>lead you</hi> into the <hi>Path</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> as you believe in it, <hi>heed</hi> it, and <hi>obey</hi> it. And this is the <hi>loving kindneſs</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to <hi>you;</hi> and <hi>his</hi> free Grace, and <hi>his</hi> Mercy, <hi>his</hi> Redemption if <hi>you</hi> will <hi>receive,</hi> and <hi>accept</hi> it; For, <hi>to as many as received him,</hi> it was, that <hi>to them he gave power to be called the Sons of God, even to as many as believe in his Name; which were born not of Blood, nor of the will of man, nor of the Fleſh, but of God;</hi> Who <hi>was in the World, and the World was made by him; and the World knew him not; who came unto his Own, and his Own recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Live</hi> not <hi>then</hi> in <hi>Pleaſures;</hi> for <hi>he that liveth in pleaſure is dead whilſt he liveth:</hi> But draw <hi>nigh</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>He</hi> will draw <hi>nigh</hi> unto <hi>you; Cleanſe your hands ye ſinners, and purifie your hearts yee double-minded: Be afflicted, and mourn, and weep; Let your laughter be turned to mourning, and your joy to heavineſs: Humble your ſelves in the ſight of the Lord, and he ſhall lift you up. Come</hi> to that which <hi>judgeth you,</hi> and <hi>love</hi> that which <hi>ſhews you,</hi> and <hi>follow</hi> that which <hi>draws you;</hi> Leaſt the <hi>hour</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Viſitation paſs <hi>Over you,</hi> and <hi>you</hi> be <hi>ſwept</hi> away by the <hi>over-flowing</hi> ſcourge which is near to <hi>come</hi> on the <hi>head</hi> of the <hi>wicked;</hi> So will <hi>ye</hi> feel <hi>my</hi> Love, and the <hi>Arms</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> which ſeeks to <hi>draw</hi> you with the <hi>Cords</hi> of a <hi>Man,</hi> with the <hi>bands</hi> of <hi>love,</hi> of which <hi>I</hi> am Witneſs; vvho ſo moves in <hi>me</hi> to you-wards; whoſe <hi>love</hi> is to <hi>you;</hi> and who am willing in <hi>any</hi> thing in the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to be ſerviceable unto <hi>your</hi> Eternal Welfare, and <hi>that</hi> which is here, which is deſired by <hi>him,</hi> who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Friend, <hi>GEO. BISHOPE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:57623:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the</hi> Arch-Biſhops <hi>(ſo called) and</hi> Biſhops, Deans <hi>and</hi> Prebends, Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors <hi>and</hi> Chor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſters, <hi>and the reſt of the</hi> Prieſthood <hi>and</hi> its <hi>Officers under</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy <hi>in</hi> theſe Nations.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>EVery Plant that my Heavenly Father hath not planted, ſhall be rooted up, <hi>ſaith</hi> Chriſt: <hi>And</hi> you <hi>being not</hi> Plants <hi>of</hi> his plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ye <hi>will be</hi> rooted <hi>up. Therefore</hi> look <hi>to</hi> your <hi>ſelves, and</hi> ſee <hi>in</hi> this <hi>your hour, whether</hi> ye <hi>be</hi> Plants <hi>which</hi> he <hi>hath</hi> ſet, <hi>which ſhall not be</hi> rooted <hi>up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Look <hi>thorough the</hi> New <hi>Teſtament (ſo called) the</hi> Scriptures <hi>of the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>and</hi> Diſciples <hi>of</hi> Jeſus, <hi>and</hi> ſee <hi>whether</hi> ye <hi>have any footing there, or in the</hi> Garden <hi>of God, where</hi> they <hi>planted who were ſent of</hi> him, <hi>who were</hi> able Miniſters of the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit; <hi>for,</hi> the Letter kills, but the Spirit giveth life, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 6.</p>
            <p>See <hi>whether ever</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>planted</hi> ſuch <hi>a thing in</hi> his <hi>Church as to be called</hi> Fathers, <hi>or</hi> Reverend Fathers, <hi>or</hi> Right Reverend Fathers? <hi>ſeeing that</hi> he <hi>ſaid unto</hi> his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> Call no man Father on the eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; for one is your Father which is in Heaven, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. 9. <hi>And ſeeing of the</hi> Lord <hi>it is ſaid—</hi>Holy &amp; Reverend is his Name, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111. 9. <hi>And whether</hi> this <hi>be</hi> Right, <hi>or</hi> in God, <hi>ſeeing it is</hi> Out <hi>of the</hi> Scriptures, <hi>and from the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Chriſt <hi>which is in</hi> God, 1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 1. 1. <hi>And</hi> none <hi>of the</hi> Gifts <hi>which when</hi> he <hi>aſcended up on high, and led Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity captive,</hi> he <hi>gave unto men, which were</hi> ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Teachers, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, till we all come in the Unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 8, <hi>to the</hi> 14. <hi>And ſeeing that</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>himſelf calls not</hi> himſelf Father, <hi>but the</hi> Son, <hi>though</hi> he <hi>be the</hi> Head <hi>of the</hi> Church, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 18? <hi>And whether</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:57623:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> Theſe <hi>be not</hi> Names <hi>of</hi> Blaſphemy? <hi>And whether the</hi> Woman <hi>W<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
               </hi> John <hi>ſaw (being carried away by the Angel which had the</hi> ſeven Vials <hi>in the</hi> Spirit <hi>into the</hi> Wilderneſs) <hi>was not</hi> ſitting <hi>on a</hi> ſcarlet colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Beaſt</hi> full <hi>of</hi> Names <hi>of</hi> Blasphemy? <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 1, 3. <hi>And whether</hi> ſhe <hi>was not</hi> drunken <hi>with the</hi> Blood <hi>of the</hi> Saints, <hi>and with the</hi> Blood <hi>of the</hi> Martyrs <hi>of</hi> Jeſus? <hi>Ver.</hi> 6. <hi>And, whether</hi> theſe <hi>be not</hi> ſome <hi>of the</hi> Names?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> look <hi>and</hi> ſee <hi>whether</hi> Lords, Arch-Biſhops, <hi>and</hi> Lord-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, <hi>or</hi> any <hi>ſuch thing be found written in the</hi> Lambs <hi>Book of</hi> Life, <hi>who exerciſe</hi> Dominion <hi>over the</hi> Lord's <hi>Herltage, and are called of</hi> men Lords? <hi>Seeing that</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>ſaith—</hi>The Kings of the Gentiles exerciſe Lordſhip over them, and they that exerciſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over them, are called Benefactors; but ye <hi>[ſhall not]</hi> be ſo; but he that is greateſt among ye, let him be as the younger; and he that is chief, as he that doth ſerve; For, whether is greater, he that ſitteth at Meat, or he that ſerveth? Is not he that ſitteth at Meat? but I am amongſt ye as he that ſerveth, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 25, 26, 27. <hi>And ſeeing that</hi> his <hi>Apoſtle ſaith—</hi>For, though there be that are called Gods, whether in Heaven, or in Earth, (as there be Gods many, and Lords many) but to Us there is but one God, the Father of whom are all things, and We in him; &amp; one Lord Jeſus, by whom are all things, and we by him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 4, 5. <hi>And ſeeing</hi> another <hi>of</hi> his <hi>Apoſtles ſaith,—</hi>The Elders which are among you I exhort, who am alſo an Elder, and a Witneſs of the ſufferings of Chriſt, and alſo a partaker of the Glory which ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed. Feed the Flock of God which is among you, taking the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight thereof, not by conſtraint, but willingly; not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind; neither as being <hi>[Lords]</hi> over Gods Heritage, but being examples to the Flock, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 23. <hi>And ſeeing the</hi> ſame <hi>Apoſtle alſo ſaith—</hi>And when the chief Shepherd <hi>(No</hi> Arch-Biſhop, <hi>no</hi> chief Shepherd <hi>of the</hi> ſheep <hi>but</hi> him) ſhall appear, we ſhall receive <hi>(who are not as</hi> [Lords] <hi>over</hi> Gods <hi>Heritage, or who</hi> Lord <hi>it not over them as aforeſaid)</hi> a Crown of glory that fadeth not away, <hi>ver.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> look <hi>and</hi> ſee <hi>whether ever the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>had the</hi> diſpoſal <hi>of</hi> Lands, <hi>otherwiſe then what</hi> every <hi>one that had a</hi> willing <hi>mind did ſell, and lay the money down at the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>feet for the</hi> relief <hi>of the</hi> Diſciples, <hi>that</hi> none <hi>amongſt</hi> them <hi>might</hi> want, <hi>and this in</hi> time <hi>of</hi> perſecution? <hi>Seeing that the</hi> Scripture <hi>ſaith—</hi>And the multitude of them that believed were of one heart, and of one ſoul, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid any of them, that ought of the things that he poſſeſſed were his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57623:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> own; but they had all things common: <hi>And that</hi> with great power gave the Apoſtles witneſs of the reſurrection of the Lord Jeſus, and great Grace was on them all; neither was there any among them that lacked; For as many as were poſſeſſors of Lands, ſold them, and brought the price of the things that were ſold, and laid them down at the Apoſtles feet: And diſtribution was made unto every man according to his need: And Joſes, who by the Apoſtles was called Barnabas, (which is by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation the Son of Conſolation) a Levite, and of the Countrey of Cyprus, having Land, ſold it, and brought the Money <hi>(not the</hi> Land) and laid it at the Apoſtles feet, <hi>Acts 4. 32. to the end. And whether</hi> Palaces <hi>and</hi> yearlie <hi>Revenues of</hi> thouſands <hi>of</hi> pounds <hi>in</hi> Land, <hi>and</hi> Houſes <hi>(which they neither</hi> ploughed <hi>for, or</hi> eared, planted <hi>or</hi> ſowed) <hi>as</hi> proper <hi>to</hi> their <hi>Place and</hi> Function; <hi>Or</hi> Earthly <hi>Dignities, or</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periorities, <hi>or</hi> Powers, <hi>or</hi> Preheminencies, <hi>or</hi> State, <hi>or</hi> Grandeur, <hi>was entailed by</hi> Chriſt <hi>to</hi> his <hi>Apoſtles and</hi> Diſciples <hi>whom</hi> he <hi>ſent forth to Miniſter, to whom</hi> he <hi>ſaid (after</hi> he <hi>was riſen from the</hi> Dead, <hi>and near aſcending)—</hi>And lo I am with you to the end of the World, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28. 20. <hi>ſeeing that</hi> himſelf <hi>alſo ſaith to</hi> Pilate—My Kingdom is not of this world; if my Kingdom were of this world, then would my ſervants fight that I ſhould not be delivered to the Jews; but now is my Kingdom not from hence, <hi>John</hi> 18. 36.<hi>—And to</hi> Peter—Put up thy ſword into the ſheath; the Cup that my Father hath given me, ſhall I not drink it? <hi>Ver.</hi> 31—Put up thy ſword <hi>(Peter)</hi> into his place; for all they that take the ſword, ſhall periſh with the ſword, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 52<hi>—And to</hi> his <hi>Diſciples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> The Foxes have holes, and the Birds of the air have Nests, but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head, <hi>Matt.</hi> 8. 20.<hi>—And,</hi> When I ſent you without purſe and ſcrip, and ſhooes, lacked ye any thing? And they ſaid, Nothing, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 35<hi>—And</hi> his <hi>Apoſtle ſaith—</hi>For though I preach the Goſpel; I have nothing to glory of; for neceſſity is laid on me, yea wo is unto me if I preach not the Goſpel: For if I do this thing <hi>(willingly)</hi> I have my reward; but if againſt my will, a Diſpenſation of the Goſpel is committed to me, what is my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward then? Verily, that when I preach the Goſpel, that I may make the Goſpel of Chriſt <hi>[without]</hi> charge; that I <hi>[abuſe]</hi> not my power in the Goſpel; for though I be free from all men, yet have I made my ſelf ſervant unto all that I might gain the more, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 16, 17, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> look <hi>and</hi> ſee <hi>whether</hi> they <hi>had any</hi> Courts <hi>or</hi> Synagogues, <hi>or</hi> places <hi>of</hi> Judicature, <hi>or ſate as</hi> Judges <hi>over</hi> Mens <hi>Perſons or</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, <hi>or had</hi> their <hi>Officers to ſummon or bring before</hi> them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57623:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>to cenſure, and to puniſh</hi> them? <hi>And whether</hi> they <hi>had, or ſought</hi> for, <hi>or uſed, or taught of</hi> ſuch <hi>a Power, or</hi> any <hi>thing like it to</hi> that, <hi>or</hi> ſucceeding <hi>ages, that might</hi> then, <hi>or</hi> hereafter, <hi>or at</hi> any <hi>time be uſed by the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>and the</hi> Diſciples <hi>of</hi> Jeſus? <hi>Seeing that</hi> he <hi>ſaith—</hi>Man, who made me a Judge, or a Divider over you? <hi>to</hi> him <hi>that ſaid,</hi> Maſter, speak to my Brother that he divide the Inheritance with me<hi>—Who was one of the</hi> company <hi>that followed</hi> him, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 13, 14. <hi>And ſeeing that</hi> he <hi>ſaid to</hi> his <hi>Diſciples—</hi>Take heed to your ſelves, for they ſhall deliver ye up to Counſels, and in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues ye ſhall be beaten, and ye ſhall be brought before Rulers and Kings for my ſake, for a teſtimony againſt them, <hi>Mark</hi> 13. 9. <hi>And that</hi> they <hi>were</hi> ſo <hi>delivered and</hi> beaten, <hi>and</hi> brought <hi>before, the</hi> Acts <hi>of the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>teſtifie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fiftly,</hi> Look <hi>and</hi> ſee <hi>whether the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>and</hi> Miniſters <hi>of</hi> Jeſus <hi>had</hi> fixed <hi>places, or</hi> ſetled <hi>ſtations or</hi> Houſes <hi>and</hi> Land <hi>appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to</hi> them <hi>by the</hi> Laws <hi>of</hi> Nations, <hi>and ſuch a</hi> Circuit <hi>of</hi> ground, <hi>and</hi> all <hi>within it, whether</hi> one <hi>or the</hi> other, <hi>to be at</hi> their <hi>Order, and this to be called</hi> their <hi>Dioceſs, or</hi> Deanary, <hi>or</hi> Pariſh, <hi>or</hi> Cure <hi>of</hi> Souls? <hi>Seeing that of</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>it is ſaid, That</hi> he went about all the Cities &amp; Villages, teaching in their Synagogues, &amp; preaching the Goſpel of the Kingdom, &amp; healing every ſickneſs, &amp; every diſeaſe among the people, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. 35. <hi>And</hi> he <hi>ſaid to</hi> his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> Freely ye have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, freely give, Heal the ſick, cleanſe the Lepers, raiſe the dead, caſt out Devils: Freely ye have received, freely give<hi>—And this was to the</hi> lost ſheep of the Houſe of Iſrael, <hi>Matt.</hi> 10. 6, 7, 8. <hi>And ſeeing</hi> his <hi>Apoſtle ſaid of</hi> himſelf <hi>and</hi> Brethren—Even to this preſent time we both hunger and thirst, and are naked, and are buffeted, and have <hi>No</hi> certain dwelling place; and labour, working with our hands, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled, we bleſs; being perſecuted, we ſuffer it; being defamed, we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat: We are made as the filth of the world, and are the off-ſcouring of all things unto this day, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 11, 12, 13. And they wandered about in ſheep-skins and goat-skins, being destitute, afflicted and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, of whom the world was not worthy. They wandered in Deſerts and in Mountains, and in Dens, and in Caves of the Earth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 37, 38 <hi>And how the</hi> Apostles <hi>went about from</hi> Nation <hi>to</hi> Nation, <hi>from</hi> City <hi>to</hi> City, <hi>preaching the</hi> Goſpel <hi>of the</hi> Kingdom, their <hi>Epiſtles and</hi> Acts <hi>manifeſt, unto which I refer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith—</hi>A Biſhop then must be blameleſs, the Husband of one Wife, vigilant, ſober, of good behaviour, given to Hoſpitality, apt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57623:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> to teach; not given to Wine; no ſtriker, nor given to filthy Lucre; but patient; not a Brawler; not Covetous; One that ruleth well his Own houſe, having his Children in ſubjection with all gravity: For, if a man know not how to rule his Own houſe, how ſhall he take Care of the Church of God?) Not a Novice, leaſt being lifted up with Pride, hee fall into the condemnation of the Devil. Moreover, he muſt have a good Report of them that are without; leaſt he fall into Reproach, and the ſnare of the Devil. Theſe things write I unto Thee <hi>(ſaith he to</hi> Timothy) hoping to come unto thee ſhortly; but if I tarry long, that thou mayſt know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelf in the Houſe of God, which is the Church of the living God, the Pillar <hi>&amp;</hi> Ground of Truth, <hi>(which</hi> no <hi>Temples made with</hi> hands <hi>are, but the</hi> Church <hi>which is in</hi> God) 1 Theſ. 1. 1. Lively ſtones built upon that ſpiritual houſe; an holy Prieſthood to offer up ſpiritual Sacrifices acceptable to God by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5.) 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>to the</hi> 8. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the</hi> ſame <hi>Apoſtle ſaith to</hi> Titus—For this Cauſe left I thee in Creet, that thou ſhouldſt ſet in order the things that are wanting, and ordain Elders in every City as I had appointed thee. If any be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, the husband of one wife, having faithful Children; not accuſed of Riot, or unruly. For a Biſhop muſt be blameleſs as the Steward of God; not ſelf-willed, not ſoon angrie; not given to wine; no ſtriker; not given to filthy lucre, but a lover of hoſpitality, a lover of good men; Sober, juſt, holy, temperate; holding faſt the faithful word as he hath been taught; that he may be able by ſound doctrine both to Exhort, and to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the gain-ſayers, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>to the</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And this</hi> Paul <hi>was</hi> an Apoſtle not of men, neither by man; but by Jeſus Chriſt, and God the Father who raiſed him from the Dead: <hi>So</hi> he <hi>ſaith himſelf,</hi> Gal. 1. 1. <hi>And</hi> Timothy <hi>had the</hi> Gift <hi>by the</hi> lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>on of the</hi> hands <hi>of the</hi> Presbytery, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 14. <hi>And the</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <hi>laid</hi> their <hi>hands on</hi> them <hi>that believed, and</hi> they <hi>received the</hi> Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 17. <hi>which</hi> Simon <hi>the</hi> Sorcerer <hi>would have bought with</hi> mony. <hi>For</hi> when Simon ſaw that through laying on of the Apoſtles hands, the Holy Ghoſt was given, he offered them mony, ſaying, Give me alſo this Power, that on whomſoever I lay hands, he may receive the Holy Ghoſt: But Peter ſaid unto him, Thy Money pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with thee, becauſe thou haſt thought the Gift of God can be purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Money: Thou haſt neither part nor lot in this matter; For thy heart is not right in the ſight of God. Repent therefore of this thy wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and pray God if perhaps the thoughs of thine heart may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57623:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> thee; for I perceive thou art in the gall of bitterneſs, and the bond of iniquity, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>to the</hi> 24 <hi>And</hi> Paul <hi>ſaid to</hi> Timothy—Lay hands ſuddenly on no ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; neither be partakers of other mens ſins; Keep thy ſelf pure, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> that <hi>Miniſtration had an</hi> End <hi>with</hi> them, <hi>and</hi> Antichriſt <hi>was</hi> then <hi>entring, and the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>propheſied of the</hi> Apoſtaſie; <hi>and</hi> Jude <hi>(ſpeaking of what was already entred, which the</hi> Prophets <hi>and the</hi> Apoſtles <hi>of the</hi> Lord Jeſus <hi>had foretold ſhould come, which was</hi> then <hi>already come) But,</hi> Beloved, <hi>(ſaith</hi> he, <hi>ver.</hi> 17.) Remember ye the words that were ſpoken by the Apoſtles of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, how that they told you there ſhould be mockers in the laſt time, which ſhould walk after their ungodly luſts. Theſe be they who ſeperate themſelves, ſenſual, having not the Spirit, <hi>ver.</hi> 18, 19. <hi>And</hi> John <hi>ſaith</hi> expreſly, <hi>That it was then the</hi> laſt <hi>time—</hi>Little Children <hi>(ſaith</hi> he) it is the <hi>[laſt]</hi> time; and as ye have heard that Antichriſt ſhall come, even Now there are many Antichriſts, whereby we know it is the <hi>[laſt]</hi> time, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2 18<hi>—And in the</hi> Revelations he <hi>ſaw the Court which was without the</hi> Temple, <hi>to be given to the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and that</hi> they <hi>ſhould</hi> tread the holy City under foot four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and two Months, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 21. <hi>And in the</hi> Overthrow <hi>of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and the</hi> Return <hi>from the</hi> Apoſtaſie, <hi>and after it,</hi> he <hi>ſpeaks not of the</hi> Return <hi>again of</hi> that <hi>Miniſtration, but of a</hi> More <hi>glorious, a</hi> City <hi>wherein the</hi> Lamb was the light thereof: <hi>And</hi> I <hi>ſaw (ſaith</hi> he) <hi>[No]</hi> Temple therein; for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb are the Temple of it. And the City had no need of the Sun, neither of the Moon to ſhine in it, for the glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb is the light thereof: And the Nations of them that are ſaved ſhall walk in the light of it, and the Kings of the Earth do bring their glory and honor unto it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 22, 23, 24. And the gates of it ſhall not be ſhut at all by day; for there ſhall be no night there. And they ſhall bring the glory and the honor of the Nations unto it: And there ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that defileth, neither whatſoever worketh an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, or maketh a lye; but they that are written ia the Lambs book of life, <hi>ver.</hi> 25, 26, 27. And all ſorrows <hi>(here)</hi> are wiped away; and God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes; and there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow nor crying; neither ſhall there be any more pain; for the former things are paſſed away. And he that ſate on the Throne, ſaid, Behold, I make all things new: And he ſaid unto me, Write, for theſe things are true and faithful, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 4, 5.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:57623:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>And,</hi> to the Lambs Wife was granted, that ſhe ſhould be arrayed in fine Linnen, clean and white; for the fine Linnen is the righteouſneſs of Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 8. <hi>And,</hi> behold the Tabernacle of God is with men, and he will dwell with them, and they ſhall be his people, and God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhall be with them, and be their God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 3. <hi>And</hi> he <hi>ſaw</hi> the holy City, the New Jeruſalem coming down from God out of Heaven, prepared as a Bride adorned for her Husband, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. And the Angel that flew through the midſt of Heaven, having the everlaſting Gospel to preach unto them that dwell on the Earth, and to every Nation, and Kindred, and Tongue, and People, ſaid with a loud Voice, Fear God, and give glory to him; for the hour of his Judgement is come; and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him who made Heaven and Earth, and the Sea, and the Fountains of Waters. And the other Angel that followed him, ſaid, Babylon is fallen, is fallen, that great City, becauſe ſhe made all Nations drink of the wrath of her Fornication, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 6, 7, 8. <hi>And</hi> rejoice over her thou Heaven, and ye holy Apoſtles and Prophets; for God hath avenged ye on her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 20. <hi>And</hi> the Victory was to the Lamb and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, who ſate on the white Horſe, whom the Armies of Heaven fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed on white Horſes, cloathed in fine Linnen, white and clean, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 11. 16. <hi>And</hi> the Angel which ſtood in the Sun, cryed with a loud voice, and ſaid to all the Fowls that flie in the midſt of Heaven, Come and gather your ſelves unto the Supper of the great God, that ye may eat the Fleſh of Kings, and the Fleſh of Captains, and the Fleſh of mighty Men, and the Fleſh of Horſes, and of them that ſit on them, and the fleſh of all men, both free and bond, both ſmall and great, <hi>ver.</hi> 17, 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And,</hi> he that testifies theſe things, ſaith, Surely I come quickly: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; Even ſo come Lord Jeſus, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 20. <hi>And</hi> behold I come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and my Reward is with me, to give every man according as his work ſhall be, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. And I Jeſus have ſent mine Angel to teſtifie unto you theſe things in the Churches: I am the Root and the Off-ſpring of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, and the bright and Morning-Star: <hi>And</hi> the Spirit and the Bride ſay Come; and let him that heareth, ſay Come; and let him that is athirſt Come, and take of the Water of Life freely, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> he ſaith unto me, Seal not the ſayings of the Propheſie of this Book; for the time is at hand: He that is unjuſt, let him be unjuſt ſtill; and he which is filthy, let him be filthy ſtill; and he that is Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, let him be righteous still; and he that is holy, let him be holy ſtill. <hi>And</hi> I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end, the first and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57623:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> the last, Bleſſed are they that do his Commandments that they may have right to the Tree of Life, aad may enter in through the gates unto the City; For without are Dogs, and Sorcerers, and Whoremongers, and Murderers, and whoſoever loveth and maketh a lye, <hi>Ver.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. For I testifie unto every man that heareth the words of the Propheſie of this Book; If any man ſhall add unto theſe things, God ſhall add unto him the plagues that are written in this Book: And if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſhall take away from the words of the Book of this Propheſie; God ſhall take away his part out of the Book of Life, and from the holy City, and from the things that are written in this Book. <hi>Ver.</hi> 18, 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſo</hi> I <hi>have ſaid to</hi> you <hi>what at preſent lies upon</hi> me <hi>from the</hi> Lord; <hi>whether</hi> you <hi>will hear or forbear; it ſhall witneſs for</hi> God <hi>againſt</hi> ye <hi>all (if</hi> ye <hi>hear not) in the</hi> Day <hi>that</hi> he <hi>ſhall ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to</hi> every <hi>man according to</hi> his <hi>Deeds. So</hi> farwel: <hi>It's</hi> my <hi>love unto</hi> you <hi>that hath drawn</hi> this <hi>for</hi> you <hi>from the</hi> movings <hi>of the</hi> Lord. <hi>It concerns</hi> you <hi>to mind whether</hi> your <hi>ſtate ſtands not</hi> ſo <hi>as is here</hi> repreſented; <hi>and to turn unto the</hi> Lord, <hi>leſt being</hi> ſo, ye <hi>be plucked up; For,</hi> every Plant tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my heavenly Father hath not plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhall be rooted up, <hi>ſaith</hi> Christ: <hi>It's that which</hi> I <hi>ſaid to</hi> ye <hi>in the beginning, in the</hi> Word <hi>of the</hi> Lord, <hi>and which</hi> I <hi>now ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> you <hi>in the</hi> ſame, <hi>at the</hi> End: <hi>And the</hi> time is near.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Geo, Biſhope.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>To the</hi> PREYSBTERY <hi>(ſo called) in</hi> theſe <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>YOu</hi> have been ſtaggering as <hi>Drunkards,</hi> and ſtarting aſide like a <hi>Deceitful</hi> Bow: <hi>You</hi> were of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and came out from the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and covenanted againſt the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and have let in the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and have (many of <hi>you)</hi> turned, and many are returning to the <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and <hi>this</hi> hath been, and <hi>is</hi> the <hi>Work</hi> of <hi>you,</hi> and of many of <hi>you,</hi> to be <hi>upwards</hi> and <hi>downwards,</hi> and <hi>back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> and <hi>forwards;</hi> now <hi>here,</hi> and now <hi>there; reeling</hi> and <hi>rouling; pinching</hi> here <hi>ſometimes,</hi> and <hi>drawing</hi> as contrary at <hi>another: You</hi> had a <hi>tender</hi> Principle once, which kept <hi>ye</hi> from evil as <hi>ye</hi> kept to it, whileſt <hi>ye</hi> were <hi>under</hi> ſufferings; but <hi>no</hi> ſooner were you <hi>free,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57623:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> but <hi>ye</hi> took the <hi>places</hi> of <hi>them</hi> that made <hi>ye</hi> to ſuffer, and ſought to make <hi>all</hi> others to ſuffer that differed from <hi>you;</hi> ye have been <hi>true</hi> to Nothing, not to <hi>your</hi> own <hi>Principles: Ye</hi> have <hi>built</hi> again the things that <hi>ye</hi> have <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> and <hi>ſo</hi> have made <hi>your</hi> ſelves Tranſgreſſors: None ſhould live but <hi>you,</hi> had <hi>ye</hi> power to <hi>your</hi> Wills; and <hi>you</hi> would live with, and <hi>above</hi> every one: The <hi>Lord</hi> hath tryed <hi>you,</hi> and let the <hi>World</hi> ſee what <hi>you</hi> would do; and <hi>his</hi> ſervants have ſuffered <hi>ſorely</hi> by <hi>you;</hi> and now <hi>he</hi> hath tryed <hi>you</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>his</hi> ſervants, and <hi>ye</hi> are fallen before <hi>them</hi> whilſt <hi>they</hi> ſtand: And <hi>yet</hi> there is not confideration with <hi>you,</hi> ſo as to think, <hi>Is not there a lie in our right hand?</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> hath born <hi>long</hi> with <hi>you,</hi> and loath <hi>he</hi> is that <hi>you</hi> ſhould periſh: <hi>He</hi> hath ſuffered <hi>ye</hi> to fall into the <hi>ſame</hi> condemnation in which <hi>others</hi> are whom <hi>you</hi> would not have <hi>free: Ye</hi> had a <hi>Day</hi> which <hi>ye</hi> long ſtrove for, and had the <hi>Door</hi> in <hi>your</hi> hands; <hi>You</hi> let it open againſt <hi>your</hi> ſelves (as it hath proved) as well as <hi>others;</hi> and it is well if ſo be it were not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in that <hi>your</hi> warineſs, leſt <hi>you</hi> being <hi>ſo,</hi> others ſhould be <hi>free:</hi> And now ſee what <hi>you</hi> have done; the <hi>Lord</hi> hath befooled <hi>you,</hi> and ſuffered <hi>ye</hi> to befool <hi>your</hi> ſelves, and to be <hi>befooled,</hi> becauſe <hi>ye</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the <hi>Counſel</hi> of the <hi>Lord;</hi> and ſo what <hi>wiſdom</hi> is in <hi>you?</hi> Whilſt <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Generation</hi> laſts, this <hi>your</hi> Work will be <hi>your</hi> ſhame, and the <hi>Lord</hi> will be againſt <hi>you</hi> whilſt <hi>ye</hi> turn not to <hi>him:</hi> For <hi>here</hi> was <hi>your</hi> miſs at firſt, <hi>Ye</hi> kept not to <hi>your</hi> principle; <hi>you</hi> turned to <hi>perſecute,</hi> who were <hi>perſecuted your</hi> ſelves; and the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ye</hi> went on in this, the more <hi>you</hi> were mad, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times was, and ſo ſaith of <hi>himſelf</hi> when <hi>he</hi> was as to the <hi>Law</hi> blameleſs, and yet without <hi>Law</hi> as to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and what <hi>your</hi> mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath brought forth upon <hi>your</hi> ſelves, judge <hi>ye.</hi> This <hi>(Friends)</hi> is to <hi>you</hi> in <hi>love,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis <hi>time</hi> for <hi>you</hi> to conſider, and to mind, that <hi>ye</hi> may ſee <hi>your</hi> ſtate, and know what the <hi>Lord</hi> is doing to <hi>you,</hi> and the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>his</hi> working: <hi>He</hi> would have <hi>you</hi> to bethink <hi>your</hi> ſelves, and ſee where <hi>ye</hi> are: He would have <hi>you</hi> to mind that in <hi>you</hi> which ſhews you <hi>your</hi> ſtate, and to hearken to the <hi>Reproof</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> the <hi>Voice</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> that <hi>your</hi> ſouls may live; and that out of <hi>all</hi> heats and <hi>raſhneſs,</hi> and <hi>anger, ye</hi> may be brought into <hi>that</hi> calm ſtate which doth unto <hi>others</hi> what it would have <hi>others</hi> do unto <hi>its ſelf.</hi> A <hi>Zeale</hi> there is in many of <hi>you,</hi> and as to <hi>God;</hi> and ſomething in ſome of <hi>you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which is <hi>ſincere</hi> to <hi>him;</hi> but <hi>your</hi> Zeal is not according
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57623:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> to <hi>Knowledge;</hi> for whileſt <hi>ye</hi> go about things in the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>man, ye</hi> cannot accompliſh the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> nor doth the <hi>ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> alwayes guide <hi>you;</hi> for then <hi>you</hi> would not hurt <hi>your</hi> principle, which was <hi>once</hi> to ſuffer, in making, and in a mind that would make others to ſuffer; nor comply to <hi>things</hi> againſt <hi>your</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple becauſe of ſuffering; For <hi>Truth</hi> is <hi>great,</hi> and the <hi>Righteous is bold as a Lyon;</hi> and the <hi>feeling</hi> of a <hi>true</hi> Witneſs of <hi>God</hi> in a <hi>Man,</hi> carries thorough, as <hi>he</hi> abides in it, <hi>all</hi> that <hi>he</hi> ſhall meet with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of it; and <hi>neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other Creature ſhall be able to ſeperate between a man and it</hi> (as <hi>he</hi> abides therewith) and that which turns from it is <hi>ſeperate,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> there is the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> &amp; where the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is, it is in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Propheſie;</hi> and that which <hi>witneſſes, propheſieth, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth,</hi> and it <hi>beareth</hi> witneſs to <hi>God</hi> in <hi>this</hi> World, and to <hi>his</hi> Truth, and that there is <hi>nothing</hi> greater than it, or <hi>more</hi> to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; yea, it is <hi>more</hi> deſirable than <hi>life;</hi> and this is made manifeſt when <hi>life</hi> and <hi>all</hi> is laid down for it; and <hi>this</hi> glorifies God, and is a Confeſſion of <hi>him</hi> before <hi>men;</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf made <hi>a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion before Pontius Pilate;</hi> And, <hi>he that confeſſes me before men, him ſhall the Son of Man alſo confeſs before the Angels of God</hi> (ſaith <hi>he) and he that denieth me before men, ſhall be denied before the Angels of God:</hi> And, <hi>to him that overcometh, will I grant to ſit with me in my Throne; even as I alſo overcame, and am ſate down with my Father in his Throne:</hi> And <hi>he</hi> that <hi>ſtarts</hi> aſide, <hi>never</hi> Overcomes; and <hi>he</hi> that doth not overcome, cannot <hi>ſit</hi> in the <hi>Throne: But the fearful, and the unbelieving, and the abominable, and Murderers, and Whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and Sorcerers, and Idolaters, and all Lyars, ſhall have their part in the Lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death:</hi> And <hi>becauſe thou haſt kept the Word of my patience, I alſo will keep thee from the hour of Temptation, which ſhall come upon all the World, to try them that dwell upon the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be <hi>ſtill</hi> therefore, and <hi>cool,</hi> and come into <hi>conſideration,</hi> and <hi>heed that</hi> in <hi>you</hi> which ſhews <hi>ye</hi> what <hi>ye</hi> have done; which ſhews <hi>ye</hi> all things that ever <hi>ye</hi> have done, as <hi>ye</hi> heed it; <hi>Is not this the Chriſt?</hi> And let the <hi>time</hi> paſt be ſufficient, wherein <hi>ye</hi> have walked accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>your</hi> own minds, and the <hi>will</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> which <hi>luſteth after envy,</hi> and return to the <hi>Lord,</hi> to the <hi>old</hi> ſtate, which kept <hi>ye</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57623:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> tender to <hi>God,</hi> and keeps <hi>ye</hi> ſtill as <hi>ye</hi> keep unto it, and made <hi>ye</hi> not to dare to do <hi>any</hi> thing againſt <hi>him;</hi> and judged <hi>ye</hi> when <hi>ye</hi> ſo did; and judges <hi>ye</hi> ſtill as <hi>ye</hi> heed it, when <hi>ye</hi> tranſgreſs it: This, this is the <hi>Way</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> the <hi>Reproof</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> and there is <hi>no</hi> other: <hi>It's</hi> from <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the <hi>chief Shepherd</hi> and <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>your Souls,</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Apoſtle)</hi> unto whom <hi>ye</hi> Return when <hi>ye</hi> are turned from going aſtray; which turns to <hi>him</hi> thoſe who are turned from going aſtray; which is that which turns from going aſtray; <hi>For ye were as ſheep going aſtray; but are now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Shepherd and Biſhop of your Souls; and when the chief Shepherd ſhall appear, ye ſhall receive a Crown of Glory that fadeth not away;</hi> ſaid <hi>Peter</hi> to the <hi>ſtrangers ſcattered throughout Pontus, Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Cappadocia, Aſia, and Bithina, elect according to the fore know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God the Father, through ſanctification of the Spirit unto obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and sprinkling of the blood of Jeſus,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 25. And to the <hi>Elders</hi> that were amongſt <hi>them, who fed the Flock of God that was amongſt them, and took the overſight thereof, not by constraint, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly; not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind; neither as being Lords over God's Heritage, but being Examples to the Flock,</hi> Chap 5. Ver. 4. This ſaid the <hi>holy Man</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friends,</hi> the <hi>tender</hi> Bowels of <hi>my</hi> Love is to <hi>that</hi> in <hi>you</hi> which ſuffers through <hi>all</hi> this heat and <hi>Luſt,</hi> and the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Wrath</hi> of <hi>Man:</hi> This <hi>Doing</hi> that which <hi>ye</hi> would not be <hi>done</hi> unto; this <hi>turning</hi> to, and <hi>for,</hi> and <hi>against;</hi> this <hi>condemning your</hi> ſelves in the <hi>things</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> allow; this <hi>building</hi> again the <hi>things</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> have <hi>destroyed;</hi> this <hi>Violence to your Brother Jacob;</hi> this <hi>rest leſs</hi> ſpirit any where but where <hi>you</hi> would <hi>your</hi> ſelves; this <hi>contradictory</hi> ſpirit which is not of <hi>God,</hi> which is <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>gentle,</hi> and <hi>eaſie to be entreated;</hi> which doth <hi>no</hi> wrong; which <hi>ſuffers</hi> wrong; which <hi>avengeth</hi> not it ſelf; whoſe is <hi>Vengeance;</hi> and who will <hi>repay it:</hi> Which when it <hi>ſuffers threatens</hi> not; which when it is <hi>reviled, reviles</hi> not again, but <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits</hi> it to <hi>him</hi> who judgeth <hi>righteouſly;</hi> and this is the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ:</hi> The <hi>Bowels</hi> of the <hi>Lord God</hi> is the ſame in <hi>me</hi> to <hi>you: I</hi> am witneſs through the <hi>ſhedding</hi> abroad of <hi>whoſe</hi> Love in <hi>my</hi> heart to <hi>his</hi> Seed in <hi>you</hi> which ſuffers, and in <hi>his</hi> moving <hi>I</hi> have written: Who am<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your <hi>Friend, who truly deſires</hi> your <hi>wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare in</hi> this <hi>world, and that which is to come:</hi> Geo. Biſhope</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57623:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the</hi> People <hi>called</hi> Independents <hi>and</hi> Baptiſts.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU <hi>muſt come down to</hi> that <hi>which</hi> witneſſeth <hi>in</hi> you, <hi>which is the</hi> Croſs <hi>of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>the</hi> Power <hi>of</hi> God <hi>to</hi> ſalvation to as many as believe; <hi>and not</hi> live <hi>above it, and yet</hi> think <hi>in</hi> your <hi>hearts that</hi> Abraham <hi>is</hi> your <hi>Father; for,</hi> if Abraham were your Father, you would do the deeds of Abraham <hi>(ſaid</hi> Chriſt <hi>to the</hi> Phariſees) but in that ye ſeek to kill me, a man which hath told ye the truth which I have heard of God, this did not Abraham. <hi>Now in that</hi> you <hi>obey not</hi> that <hi>which</hi> witneſſeth <hi>in</hi> you, <hi>nor believe in it,</hi> you <hi>do not the</hi> deeds <hi>of</hi> Abraham; <hi>for,</hi> Abraham <hi>(ſaid</hi> he) ſaw my day, and rejoiced; and before Abraham was, I am. <hi>Now in</hi> this <hi>Day</hi> he <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, or</hi> he <hi>could not have ſeen it; and</hi> his <hi>day</hi> he <hi>ſaw, or</hi> he <hi>could not have rejoiced; and</hi> his <hi>Deeds</hi> he <hi>did,</hi> whoſe <hi>Day</hi> he <hi>ſaw, or</hi> he <hi>could not have believed: For,</hi> I <hi>believed, therefore</hi> I <hi>ſpake: And</hi> I <hi>know</hi> Abraham that he will command his Children and his Houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord to do Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Judgement, that the Lord may bring upon Abraham that which he hath ſpoken of him; <hi>and</hi> thou meeteſt him that rejoiceth and worketh righteouſneſs. <hi>So the</hi> Joy <hi>is in</hi> that <hi>which</hi> worketh righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>and that which</hi> worketh righteouſneſs <hi>is of</hi> Abraham; <hi>and</hi> that <hi>which doth the</hi> deeds <hi>of</hi> Abraham, <hi>ſeeth</hi> his <hi>day, and rejoiceth; and</hi> that <hi>killeth not, nor ſeeks to</hi> kill a man that tells ye the truth he hath heard of God. This did not Abraham.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now</hi> (Friends) <hi>to be</hi> plain <hi>and</hi> ſhort <hi>with</hi> you; You <hi>are the</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren <hi>of</hi> Abraham <hi>no farther, and no longer than</hi> ye <hi>do the</hi> deeds <hi>of</hi> Abraham; <hi>but</hi> his <hi>Children</hi> ye <hi>are whoſe</hi> works ye <hi>do: And therefore ſaid</hi> John <hi>to the</hi> Phariſees <hi>who came to</hi> his <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> O Generation of Vipers, who hath forewarned ye to flee from the wrath to come? Bring forth therefore, fruits meet for repentance; and think not to ſay in your ſelves, that we have Abraham to our Father; for I ſay unto you, God is able of theſe ſtones to raiſe up Children unto Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham. And now alſo the Axe is laid to the Root of the Tree; therefore every Tree that bringeth not forth <hi>[good]</hi> fruit, is hewn down, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57623:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> caſt into the fire. I indeed, baptize you with water unto Repentance; but he that cometh after me, is mightier then I, whoſe ſhooes I am not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to bear, he ſhall baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt and with fire; whoſe Fan is in his hand; and he will throughly purge his floor, and gather his Wheat into his Garner; but he will <hi>[burn up the Chaff]</hi> with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So</hi> ſee <hi>(Friends) what</hi> fruit you <hi>bear, and</hi> whoſe <hi>Works</hi> ye <hi>do;</hi> Whoſe <hi>Tree</hi> ye <hi>are of; for, as is the</hi> Tree, <hi>ſo is the</hi> fruit; <hi>and as is the</hi> Fruit, <hi>ſo is the</hi> Tree: <hi>And if the</hi> Tree <hi>be</hi> evil, <hi>the</hi> Fruit <hi>is</hi> ſo; <hi>and if the</hi> Fruit <hi>be</hi> evil, <hi>the</hi> Tree <hi>is</hi> ſo: <hi>And</hi> every Tree that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not forth <hi>[good]</hi> fruit, is hewn down, and caſt into the fire. <hi>And ſee</hi> (Friends) <hi>whether</hi> ye <hi>are</hi> Chaff <hi>or</hi> Wheat: <hi>For to this</hi> ye <hi>muſt come, if ever it be well with</hi> you: <hi>For</hi> he will thoroughly purge his Floor, <hi>whoſe</hi> Fan <hi>is in</hi> his <hi>hand, who</hi> baptizeth <hi>with the</hi> Holy Ghoſt <hi>and with</hi> Fire; <hi>whoſe</hi> ſhooes (John <hi>ſaith)</hi> he <hi>was not</hi> worthy <hi>to bear, and that</hi> he <hi>was</hi> mightier <hi>then</hi> he <hi>who came to</hi> baptize <hi>with</hi> water <hi>unto</hi> Repentance; <hi>and</hi> he <hi>will</hi> gather his Wheat into the Garner, and burn up the Chaff with unquenchable fire, <hi>as hath been declared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In</hi> Bowels <hi>of</hi> tender <hi>love</hi> I <hi>write</hi> theſe <hi>things, as being moved of the</hi> Lord <hi>for</hi> his <hi>Seed's ſake in</hi> you, <hi>that</hi> ye <hi>be not deceived in a</hi> wrong <hi>apprehenſion of</hi> your <hi>ſtate, as in</hi> another, <hi>when</hi> you <hi>are not as</hi> he <hi>is in</hi> your <hi>ſelves: For,</hi> if whileſt we ſeek to be juſtified by Chriſt, we our ſelves are found ſinners <hi>(ſaith</hi> Paul) is therefore Chriſt the Miniſter of ſin? God forbid: For if I build again the things that I have deſtroyed, I make my ſelf a Tranſgreſſor. <hi>And</hi> if any man be in Chriſt Jeſus, he is a new Creature. Old things are paſſed away; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all things are become new; <hi>for,</hi> as he is, ſo muſt be that which is in him: <hi>For,</hi> What fellowſhip hath Righteouſneſs with Unrighteouſneſs? And what Communion hath Light with Darkneſs? And what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord hath Chriſt with Belial? Or what part hath he that believeth, with an Infidel? And what agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols? For ye are the Temple of the living God <hi>(ſaid</hi> Paul <hi>to the</hi> Corinthians, <hi>the</hi> Church <hi>there)</hi> as God hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walk in them, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people. <hi>And</hi> he that doth righteouſneſs <hi>(ſaith</hi> John) is righteous, as he is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: <hi>And,</hi> every man that hath this hope in him, purifies himſelf as he is pure; For as he is, ſo are we in <hi>[this]</hi> World: <hi>And</hi> whoſoever ſinneth, hath neither ſeen him, nor known him: <hi>And</hi> the Temple of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57623:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> God is holy, whoſe Temple ye are: <hi>And,</hi> if any man defile the Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy. <hi>And,</hi> know ye not that ye are the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you, <hi>ſaith</hi> Paul <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the ſame</hi> Church? <hi>And</hi> he that is born of God, doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin, for his Seed remaineth in him, and he cannot ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is born of God, He that committeth ſin is of the Devil, for the Devil ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nneth from the beginning. For this purpoſe the Son of God was manifeſted, that he might deſtroy the works of the Devil. Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever abideth in him, ſinneth not. Little Children, let no man deceive you, he that doth righteouſneſs is righteous as he is righteous. In this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the Devil: Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <hi>[doth]</hi> not righteouſneſs, is <hi>[not]</hi> of God, neither he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not his Brother, <hi>ſaith</hi> John <hi>again in</hi> his firſt <hi>Epiſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now</hi> (Friends) <hi>theſe things</hi> I <hi>have written unto</hi> you <hi>(as</hi> I <hi>have ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that</hi> ye <hi>may not be deceived; for while</hi> ye <hi>think to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by</hi> Christ, <hi>and yet keep a</hi> liberty <hi>in</hi> ſome <hi>things to</hi> tranſgreſs, <hi>and in</hi> ſome <hi>things to</hi> heed <hi>the</hi> Witneſs <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>and believe not in</hi> him <hi>in</hi> that <hi>which</hi> witneſſeth <hi>that</hi> that <hi>is</hi> He; ye will dye in your ſins. Except ye believe that I am he <hi>(ſaid</hi> he <hi>to the</hi> Phariſees) ye ſhall die in your ſins: <hi>For,</hi> he became the Author of eternal ſalvation to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as obey him, even to as many as believe in his Name: <hi>And this is</hi> his <hi>Name,</hi> The true and faithful Witneſs<hi>—Unto which anſwers</hi> that <hi>of</hi> him <hi>in the</hi> Conſcience, <hi>and by which</hi> he <hi>will judge</hi> all <hi>men, and</hi> they <hi>ſhall be left</hi> without <hi>excuſe; For,</hi> if ye were blind <hi>(ſaid</hi> he <hi>to the</hi> Phariſees) ye ſhould have no ſin; but now ye ſay. We ſee, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your ſin remaineth. <hi>And,</hi> he was manifest to take away ſin. <hi>And</hi> for this purpoſe was the Son of God made manifest, that he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the works of the Devil. <hi>And</hi> ſin <hi>is the</hi> work <hi>of the</hi> Devil. <hi>And</hi> he gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purifie unto himſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good works. <hi>Now how can</hi> theſe <hi>things be, and</hi> Men <hi>abide in</hi> ſin, <hi>and that to</hi> their <hi>Death? And how are</hi> they <hi>purged and purified from</hi> ſin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in</hi> ſin? <hi>And how are</hi> they <hi>juſtified that are</hi> condemned <hi>for</hi> ſin? <hi>And how are</hi> their <hi>ſins</hi> taken <hi>away, whoſe</hi> ſin <hi>remain? And how are</hi> they <hi>in</hi> Christ Jeſus <hi>who are not</hi> new <hi>Creatures? And how are</hi> they <hi>as he is in</hi> this <hi>world, who</hi> ſin <hi>while</hi> they <hi>are in</hi> this <hi>world? And how are</hi> they <hi>righteous even as</hi> he <hi>is righteous, who do</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs? <hi>and all</hi> unrighteouſneſs <hi>is</hi> ſin: <hi>And how do</hi> they <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie</hi> themſelves <hi>as</hi> he <hi>is pure, who abide in</hi> ſin! <hi>And how is</hi> he <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57623:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>the</hi> Author <hi>of</hi> Eternal <hi>Salvation to</hi> them <hi>who neither obey</hi> him, <hi>nor believe in</hi> his <hi>Name? And how are</hi> old <hi>things paſſed away, when they are</hi> there <hi>ſtill? And how are</hi> all <hi>things become</hi> new, <hi>when there is the</hi> old? <hi>And how can</hi> that <hi>be in</hi> him, <hi>which hath neither</hi> ſeen him, <hi>nor</hi> known him? <hi>And how can</hi> that <hi>have</hi> Eternal life, <hi>which will not</hi> come <hi>to</hi> him?</p>
            <p>Friends, <hi>Theſe things are</hi> deep <hi>and</hi> weighty, <hi>and it behoves</hi> ye <hi>to conſider whilſt</hi> ye <hi>have time, for the</hi> Door <hi>is</hi> near <hi>ſhutting, and the</hi> Lord <hi>is at hand, to</hi> render unto every man according to his [work] <hi>and as</hi> your <hi>works are, ſo will be</hi> your <hi>reward. So 'tis high time to look about</hi> you, <hi>that</hi> ye <hi>may be ſure of</hi> your <hi>works, and that</hi> they <hi>be wrought in</hi> God; <hi>For, the</hi> Night is at hand wherein none can work; <hi>but</hi> every <hi>man muſt be tried according to</hi> his <hi>work, for what</hi> he <hi>hath, not what hath</hi> another. <hi>The</hi> Lord <hi>hath long wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on</hi> you, <hi>and</hi> his <hi>preſence hath been amongſt</hi> ye, <hi>and</hi> he <hi>hath been with</hi> you <hi>whilſt</hi> ye <hi>have been with</hi> him. He <hi>is now come whom</hi> ye <hi>knew not, though</hi> he <hi>was with</hi> you: <hi>The</hi> times of this ignorance God winked at; now he commands men every where to repent, becauſe he hath appointed a Day in the which he will judge the World in righteouſneſs by that man whom he hath ordained, whereof he hath given aſſurance unto all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead; and if Chriſt be not riſen, then are ye yet in your ſins: But Chriſt is riſen, and is become the firſt fruits of them that ſlept. <hi>And that</hi> he <hi>is riſen, appears by</hi> his <hi>Witneſs in</hi> all <hi>men, which</hi> teſtifies <hi>to</hi> all, <hi>and</hi> witneſſeth <hi>to</hi> his <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngdom, which is an</hi> everlaſting <hi>Kingdom; and to</hi> his <hi>Dominion, which ſhall</hi> never <hi>have end. And it bears</hi> witneſs <hi>to the</hi> Lord, <hi>that</hi> he <hi>deſireth not the</hi> death <hi>of a</hi> ſinner, <hi>but rather that</hi> he <hi>may return and live (as</hi> he <hi>hath ſworn) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is</hi> that <hi>of</hi> him <hi>in</hi> every <hi>one that ſeeks</hi> them <hi>to live; over which</hi> Death <hi>hath</hi> no <hi>more dominion: For, in that</hi> he <hi>is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi> Death <hi>hath</hi> no <hi>more dominion over</hi> him, <hi>but</hi> he <hi>liveth unto</hi> God: <hi>And,</hi> he is the propitiation for our ſins: <hi>By</hi> Faith <hi>in whoſe Blood</hi> we have acceſs unto God by this grace in which we ſtand, and rejoice in hope of the glory of God. Foraſmuch then as Christ hath ſuffered in the fleſh, arm your ſelves with the ſame mind; for he that hath ſuffered in the fleſh, hath ceaſed from ſin, that he no longer ſhould live the rest of his time in the fleſh, in the lusts of men, but to the will of God.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57623:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>And ſo</hi> (Friends) I <hi>leave</hi> you <hi>to the</hi> Witneſs <hi>of</hi> God <hi>to</hi> anſwer <hi>to</hi> me <hi>in</hi> this <hi>thing (which will</hi> anſwer <hi>to</hi> me <hi>if</hi> you <hi>heed it,</hi> you <hi>will hear</hi> it) <hi>for</hi> I <hi>am moved of the</hi> Lord <hi>unto</hi> this <hi>in</hi> bowels <hi>of</hi> Love, <hi>and it wil leave</hi> you <hi>without excuſe. So</hi> Farwell: My <hi>Love is to the</hi> Seed <hi>of</hi> God <hi>in</hi> you, <hi>who am known to</hi> many <hi>of</hi> you <hi>by the</hi> Name <hi>of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GEO. BISHOPE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>To the</hi> People <hi>of</hi> theſe <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>YOu</hi> have had <hi>Long</hi> and <hi>Great</hi> Warning; the <hi>Lord</hi> hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up from amongſt <hi>ye of your Sons,</hi> and of <hi>your Daughters;</hi> of <hi>your ſervants,</hi> and of <hi>your Neighbours,</hi> faithful Witneſſes unto <hi>his</hi> Name; who by <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Writing; Converſation</hi> and <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; Doing</hi> and <hi>Suffering</hi> have teſtified of <hi>his Day</hi> that is come; wherein <hi>he</hi> will judge <hi>every</hi> one according to <hi>his</hi> Works; and that the <hi>Axe</hi> is laid to the <hi>Root</hi> of the <hi>Tree;</hi> and <hi>every</hi> Tree that brings not forth <hi>good</hi> fruit, is hewen down, and caſt into the <hi>fire;</hi> and therefore <hi>he</hi> warned <hi>you</hi> by <hi>them all</hi> to bring forth <hi>fruits</hi> meet for <hi>Repentance</hi> whilſt the <hi>Door</hi> was open, and whilſt he called; that when <hi>you</hi> ſhould call in the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>your</hi> diſtreſs, <hi>he</hi> might <hi>ariſe</hi> and <hi>deliver you.</hi> And by <hi>them he</hi> ſhewed <hi>you</hi> the <hi>way</hi> unto <hi>himſelf,</hi> even by hearkning to, and obeying <hi>that</hi> of <hi>him</hi> within <hi>every</hi> one of <hi>you;</hi> which ſhewed <hi>ye</hi> evil, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd and judged <hi>you,</hi> and ſhewed to <hi>you</hi> what <hi>ye</hi> ſhould do; by which the <hi>Holy</hi> Men of <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Old</hi> drew near unto, and were drawn to the <hi>Lord;</hi> and by which thoſe of <hi>your</hi> Sons and Daughters, <hi>Servants</hi> and <hi>Neighbours,</hi> who have teſtified as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and remained faithful have drawn near, and were brought to the <hi>Lord,</hi> and have felt <hi>his</hi> power to give <hi>them</hi> Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>evil,</hi> and the corrupt Converſation in which <hi>they</hi> lived whilſt <hi>they</hi> were ignorant of, and believed not in <hi>him</hi> who witneſſed in <hi>them;</hi> who is the <hi>Power of God to ſalvation</hi> to as <hi>many</hi> as obey <hi>him;</hi> even to as <hi>many</hi> as believe in <hi>his</hi> Name.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:57623:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Now, <hi>Friends,</hi> after all <hi>this</hi> Warning, and <hi>gracious</hi> Viſitation the <hi>Lord</hi> hath <hi>long</hi> waited to ſee whether <hi>ye</hi> would turn to that which witneſſeth in <hi>you;</hi> which is of <hi>God,</hi> and obey it, that <hi>your</hi> ſouls may <hi>live,</hi> and be <hi>redeemed</hi> out of <hi>Death,</hi> and from the <hi>bondage</hi> of <hi>Corruption,</hi> In which <hi>you</hi> are who are <hi>ſervants</hi> unto <hi>ſin.</hi> For as <hi>many</hi> as are led by <hi>ſin,</hi> are <hi>ſervants</hi> unto <hi>ſin;</hi> and as <hi>many</hi> as are <hi>ſervants</hi> unto <hi>ſin,</hi> are in <hi>bondage</hi> to <hi>ſin;</hi> and as many as are in <hi>bondage</hi> to <hi>ſin,</hi> are in <hi>Death,</hi> and the <hi>Son</hi> hath not made <hi>them</hi> free; For if the <hi>Son</hi> make <hi>ye free, then are ye free indeed,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and the <hi>Truth</hi> makes <hi>free,</hi> and this is <hi>Truth, To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the onely true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent;</hi> and <hi>that</hi> of <hi>him</hi> in <hi>you</hi> which ſhews <hi>ye your</hi> ſtate, and <hi>your</hi> condition, and <hi>your</hi> Enemy, and <hi>his</hi> working, and where <hi>ye</hi> are, and how <hi>ye</hi> are fallen, and gone Out of the <hi>Way;</hi> Is that which is come to redeem <hi>you</hi> out of <hi>that</hi> ſtate; and to deliver <hi>you</hi> from <hi>your</hi> Enemy, and to recover <hi>you</hi> back again, and <hi>to guide your feet in the way of Peace,</hi> that <hi>your</hi> Souls may have <hi>reſt</hi> with <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>this you</hi> know <hi>every</hi> one of <hi>you, You</hi> cannot <hi>stifle</hi> it; It's <hi>too</hi> late to do it; the <hi>Lord</hi> hath reached to <hi>his</hi> Witneſs in <hi>you;</hi> and hath given <hi>you</hi> to ſee all <hi>this,</hi> and how <hi>you</hi> ſhould hearken to that of <hi>him</hi> in <hi>you</hi> which ſhews <hi>ye</hi> all this, and the <hi>ſecrets</hi> of <hi>your</hi> hearts, and ſearcheth <hi>your</hi> hearts, and trieth <hi>your</hi> reins, and ſhews <hi>you</hi> the compaſs and end of <hi>your</hi> actions, and that <hi>ye</hi> ſhould <hi>do</hi> none iniquity, it tells <hi>you</hi> in ſecret. Now <hi>that</hi> which ſhews <hi>ye</hi> this, is <hi>greater</hi> then <hi>all;</hi> for, <hi>it</hi> ſhould never ſhine in <hi>your</hi> Conſciences, &amp; ſhew <hi>you</hi> this, &amp; the <hi>way</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> could that which hath <hi>you</hi> in Captivity <hi>keep</hi> it out, &amp; it concerns <hi>you</hi> to heed, and to have heeded <hi>this,</hi> that ſo the <hi>Lord's</hi> loving-kindneſs might not be in <hi>vain</hi> as to <hi>you,</hi> nor the <hi>ſtriving</hi> of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> nor the <hi>stretching</hi> forth of <hi>his</hi> Arms to <hi>draw</hi> and <hi>gather you;</hi> for <hi>this</hi> of a <hi>truth I</hi> have to ſay unto <hi>you,</hi> That <hi>ye</hi> have <hi>all</hi> need of <hi>him,</hi> &amp; of <hi>his</hi> mercy; not that <hi>he</hi> hath need of <hi>you:</hi> And <hi>he</hi> might have left <hi>ye</hi> all in the ſtate wherein <hi>ye</hi> were by Nature, even <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Wrath,</hi> and never have ſhewn <hi>ye</hi> where <hi>you</hi> were, or that <hi>ye</hi> were ſinners; or, in <hi>ſuch</hi> a ſtate; nor <hi>your</hi> Enemy; nor <hi>what</hi> an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my <hi>he</hi> is, until <hi>ye</hi> come to feel <hi>his</hi> Wrath, and to be tumbled into the <hi>Pit,</hi> out of which <hi>none</hi> that goes, ever comes. But <hi>he</hi> hath viſited <hi>you,</hi> and ſhewn <hi>you</hi> what is good, <hi>To do justly, to</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:57623:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>love mercy, and to walk humbly with the Lord;</hi> and ſomething hath ſtriven in <hi>you</hi> ſince the time <hi>you</hi> could remember, and ſhew'd <hi>you</hi> evil, and judg'd <hi>you</hi> for evil; yet it <hi>ye</hi> have not obeyed, but have been conformed to the <hi>World,</hi> and to the <hi>Faſhions</hi> and <hi>Customes</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> which are evil, as <hi>you</hi> have been led, and <hi>you</hi> have done the thing which <hi>ye</hi> have been convinc't is evil; although <hi>ye</hi> have been judged in <hi>your</hi> ſelves, that <hi>that</hi> was evil; and knew that that was the <hi>Judgement</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and that <hi>his</hi> Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is <hi>Just:</hi> And <hi>you</hi> know that the things which <hi>ye</hi> have been <hi>convinced</hi> of to be evil <hi>many</hi> years ago, and have been <hi>judged<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> for it, do yet <hi>remain</hi> with <hi>you,</hi> and that the <hi>Lord</hi> hath been <hi>rejected,</hi> and his <hi>drawings ſlighted,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Enemy and <hi>yours</hi> heeded, &amp; that <hi>ye</hi> have <hi>refuſed</hi> to come to <hi>him</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> might have <hi>life,</hi> to the <hi>light which makes manifest; for whatſoever is made manifest, is made manifeſt by the Light;</hi> and, <hi>I am the Light of the world</hi> (ſaith <hi>he) he that believeth in me, ſhall not abide in darkneſs, but ſhall have the light of life.</hi> And, <hi>this is the condemnation, that Light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather then light, becauſe their deeds are Evil.</hi> And, <hi>in him was life</hi> (ſaith <hi>John) and the Life was the Light of men; that is the true Light that lighte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h every man that cometh into the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this <hi>you</hi> know (as <hi>I</hi> have ſaid) <hi>viz.</hi> That there is <hi>ſuch</hi> a thing in <hi>you,</hi> and the <hi>thing</hi> in <hi>you</hi> witneſſes that it is ſo; and <hi>ye</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not blot it out; and that <hi>ye</hi> have diſobeyed it, and do diſobey it; and that it ſuffers in <hi>you;</hi> and yet <hi>you</hi> are <hi>vain,</hi> and <hi>proud,</hi> and <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and <hi>lustful,</hi> and do <hi>conform</hi> to <hi>this</hi> world, and do <hi>lye,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi> and <hi>cheat,</hi> and <hi>cozen,</hi> and <hi>ſwear,</hi> and are <hi>drunk,</hi> and do <hi>ſpend</hi> the <hi>creatures</hi> upon <hi>your</hi> Luſts; and do <hi>hate,</hi> and do <hi>kill,</hi> and do <hi>ſteal,</hi> and do <hi>commit</hi> Adultery, and do covet <hi>your</hi> Neighbours Goods, and do <hi>grind</hi> the Faces of the <hi>Poor,</hi> and <hi>oppreſs</hi> and <hi>ſmite</hi> with the <hi>Fiſt</hi> of <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> and take the <hi>Name</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in vain; and do go beyond one <hi>another</hi> in dealing where <hi>you</hi> would not be done <hi>ſo</hi> to <hi>your</hi> ſelves: Theſe things <hi>I</hi> ſay <hi>ye</hi> know are ſo; and yet <hi>ye</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlnue as <hi>ye</hi> were before; and <hi>theſe</hi> things continue in <hi>you;</hi> and <hi>ye</hi> think the <hi>Lord</hi> is ſuch a <hi>one</hi> as <hi>your</hi> ſelves, becauſe <hi>he</hi> holds <hi>his</hi> peace and hath a <hi>long</hi> time been ſilent, and hath not brought <hi>his</hi> Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon <hi>you;</hi> nor cauſed <hi>ye</hi> to feel the <hi>Power</hi> of his Wrath; and <hi>ye</hi> think to <hi>morrow</hi> ſhall be as to <hi>day,</hi> and much <hi>more</hi> abundant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Lord</hi> hath been <hi>long-ſuffering, ſlow to anger, abundant in</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57623:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>goodneſs</hi> and <hi>truth;</hi> not willing that any of <hi>you</hi> ſhould <hi>die,</hi> but rather that <hi>ye</hi> ſhould return and live.</p>
            <p>And this is the Uſe <hi>ye</hi> have made (many of <hi>you)</hi> of <hi>his</hi> loving kindneſs, and <hi>mercy, his</hi> long-ſuffering and <hi>forbearance;</hi> to add <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> to <hi>Thirſt, Iniquity</hi> unto <hi>iniquity,</hi> and to draw <hi>iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> with <hi>Cart-ropes</hi> of <hi>Vanity:</hi> And <hi>you</hi> cannot think (many of <hi>you)</hi> how to be <hi>Vain enough,</hi> nor <hi>Drunken enough;</hi> nor <hi>Proud enough;</hi> nor <hi>Voluptuous enough,</hi> nor <hi>Conſumptive</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Creatures <hi>enough;</hi> and <hi>ye declare your ſin as Sodom; the ſhew of your countenance witneſſes it againſt ye;</hi> and <hi>ye</hi> think that <hi>ye</hi> are delivered to commit <hi>all</hi> theſe Abominations; as if the <hi>Lord</hi> took Pleaſure in <hi>theſe</hi> things, or delighted in <hi>them;</hi> and as if <hi>this</hi> was a <hi>Retribution</hi> Equivalent to <hi>him</hi> for <hi>all your</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances; and as if it were the <hi>ſumme,</hi> and the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>all his</hi> working; and as if the <hi>more</hi> vain and <hi>wicked ye</hi> are, the more <hi>ye</hi> give <hi>him</hi> thanks; and the more <hi>ye</hi> anſwer the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>his</hi> working<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo <hi>ye</hi> laviſh out <hi>your</hi> ſelves in <hi>all riot</hi> and <hi>exceſs,</hi> as <hi>he</hi> hath been liberal to <hi>you</hi> in his Mercies; as if <hi>this</hi> were the <hi>thing</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> aimed at in <hi>all,</hi> and expected as the <hi>Return</hi> of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and <hi>ye</hi> have been <hi>very</hi> bold (many of <hi>you)</hi> thus to do, notwithſtanding that <hi>that</hi> of <hi>him</hi> in <hi>you</hi> tells <hi>you</hi> (and <hi>ye</hi> know it) that <hi>ye</hi> ſhould do otherwiſe, and judgeth <hi>ye;</hi> and ſo <hi>ye</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn <hi>your</hi> own Mercies, and provoke the <hi>Lord</hi> to be <hi>jealous</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Name and Glory, which <hi>he</hi> hath ſaid <hi>he</hi> will not give unto <hi>another;</hi> and to make <hi>ye</hi> examples to the <hi>ages</hi> to come of his judgments, as <hi>he</hi> hath made <hi>ye</hi> patterns of <hi>his</hi> mercies; and to let the <hi>world</hi> know, by what <hi>he</hi> ſhal do unto <hi>you,</hi> that he is a <hi>God</hi> that delighteth not in <hi>iniquity,</hi> nor ſhall <hi>ſin</hi> come near <hi>his</hi> Dwelling; but that <hi>he</hi> is <hi>holy,</hi> and will be ſanctified in <hi>all</hi> that draw near <hi>him,</hi> &amp; be had in <hi>Reverence</hi> by <hi>all</hi> that are about <hi>him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this <hi>I am</hi> moved of the <hi>Lord God</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> to warn <hi>ye of;</hi> and to let <hi>ye</hi> know that <hi>he</hi> will appear againſt <hi>you;</hi> and that <hi>he</hi> will vindicate <hi>his</hi> Name and his Glory in what <hi>he</hi> ſhall do unto <hi>you;</hi> and that <hi>he</hi> is drawing near to <hi>plead</hi> with <hi>you,</hi> and to render unto <hi>you</hi> according to <hi>your</hi> works.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the <hi>Bowels</hi> of <hi>Love, I</hi> exhort and <hi>warn you</hi> to break off <hi>your ſins by righteouſneſs, and your iniquities by ſhewing mercy to the Poor; if ſo be there may be yet a lengthening of your tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility.</hi> For this <hi>I</hi> have received from the <hi>Lord God;</hi> whoſe <hi>Word</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:57623:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> and <hi>Warning</hi> it is, that <hi>he</hi> will make a <hi>ſhort work</hi> with <hi>you;</hi> and after <hi>ye</hi> have filled up the <hi>meaſure</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Iniquity, (which <hi>he</hi> will ſuffer <hi>ye</hi> to <hi>fulfil,</hi> if ſo be yet <hi>ye</hi> ſhall not hearken, nor yield obedience to <hi>his</hi> voice, nor <hi>depart</hi> from <hi>iniquity,</hi> nor <hi>chooſe</hi> to <hi>do</hi> the <hi>thing</hi> that is <hi>good,</hi> which <hi>that</hi> of <hi>him</hi> ſhews <hi>ye</hi> in <hi>your</hi> hearts) <hi>He</hi> will cut <hi>ye</hi> Down, and <hi>his</hi> judgments ſhall come upon <hi>you;</hi> and <hi>ye</hi> ſhall know that <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning unto <hi>you,</hi> through <hi>his</hi> ſervant</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GEO. BISHOPE.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> 
                  <date>25 8 Month, 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57623:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
